<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>D. C. Stephenson</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>239246</id>
    <revision>
      <id>943109243</id>
      <parentid>943052345</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-02-28T22:02:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Keith D</username>
        <id>2278355</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Early life and education */ Add missing pipe</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="18472" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox criminal
| name               = D. C. Stephenson
| image_name         = D._C._Stephenson_Grand_Dragon_of_the_Klu_Klux_Klan_in_Indiana,_c_1922.jpg
| image_caption      = Stephenson in 1992
| birth_name         = David Curtiss Stephenson
| birth_date         = {{Birth-date|21 August 1891|August 21, 1891}}
| birth_place        = [[Houston|Houston, Texas]], United States
| death_date         = {{Death-date|28 June 1966|June 28, 1966}} (aged 74)
| death_place        = [[Jonesborough, Tennessee]], United States
| charge             = [[second-degree murder]]&lt;br&gt;[[rape]]&lt;br&gt;[[kidnapping]]&lt;br&gt;[[conspiracy]]
| conviction_penalty = Life in prison (1925)
| conviction_status  = Paroled (1950; 1956)
| occupation         = [[salesman]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ku Klux Klan]] [[Grand Dragon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Linotype machine|linotype]] operator&lt;br&gt;newspaper [[reporter]]
| spouse             = (1) Nettie Hamilton, &lt;br&gt;(2) Violet Carroll, &lt;br&gt;(3) Martha Dickenson, &lt;br&gt;(4) Martha Murray Sutton
| children           = 1
}}
'''David Curtiss "Steve" Stephenson''' (August 21, 1891 &amp;ndash; June 28, 1966) was a convicted murderer and rapist, who in 1923 was appointed [[Grand Dragon]] of the [[Indiana Klan|branch of the Ku Klux Klan]] in [[Indiana]] and head of Klan recruiting for seven other states. Later that year, he led those groups to independence from the [[Ku Klux Klan|national KKK organization]]. Amassing wealth and political power in Indiana politics, he was one of the most prominent national Klan leaders. "He was viewed as responsible for reviving the Klan and widening its base, and considered the most powerful man in Indiana".&lt;ref name=CL&gt;Criminal Law Cases and Materials, 7th ed. 2012, John Kaplan, Robert Weisberg, Guyora Binder&lt;/ref&gt; He had close relationships with numerous Indiana politicians, especially Governor [[Edward L. Jackson]].

In ''[[Stephenson v. State]]'' (1925) Stephenson was tried for and convicted of the abduction, rape, and murder of a young white woman, [[Madge Oberholtzer]], a state education official. His trial, conviction and imprisonment ended the portrayal of Klan leaders as law abiding. The case destroyed the Klan as a political force in Indiana, and significantly damaged its standing nationally.&lt;ref name=CL/&gt; Denied a pardon by Governor Jackson, in 1927 he started talking with reporters for the ''[[Indianapolis Times]]'' and released a list of elected and other officials who had been in the pay of the Klan. This led to a wave of indictments in Indiana, more national scandals, the rapid loss of tens of thousands of members, and the end of the second wave of Klan activity in the late 1920s.

==Early life and education==
Stephenson was born in [[Houston]], [[Texas]] on August 21, 1891, and moved as a child with his family to [[Maysville, Oklahoma]]. After some public schooling, he started work as a printer's apprentice and was active in the [[Populist Party of America|Populist Party]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.indianahistory.org/wp-content/uploads/d-c-stephenson-collection-1922-1978.pdf|title=D. C. Stephenson Collection, 1922-1978|website=|publisher=Indiana Historical Society|access-date=28 February 2020|url-status=live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[World War I]], he enlisted in the [[United States Army|Army]] and completed officers' training. He never served overseas, but his training proved useful when he organized and led groups.&lt;ref name="Moore"/&gt;

==Klansman==

{{see also|Indiana Klan}}
In 1920 at the age of 29, he moved to [[Evansville, Indiana]], where he worked for a retail coal company. He joined the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] and in 1922, ran unsuccessfully for a Democratic [[United States House of Representatives|Congressional]] nomination.&lt;ref&gt;Gray, Ralph D.; ''Indiana History: A Book of Readings'' (1995), p 306. Indiana: Indiana University Press. {{ISBN|0-253-32629-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He was said to have already "married and abandoned two wives" before settling in Evansville.&lt;ref name="Moore"&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=a1eSbL0kxk8C&amp;pg=PA13&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=4#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Leonard J. Moore, ''Citizen Klansmen: The Ku Klux Klan in Indiana, 1921-1928''], Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1997, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

Joseph M. Huffington, whom the [[Ku Klux Klan]] had sent from Texas as an agent for organizing in Evansville, recruited Stephenson to the group's inner circle. The historian Leonard Moore characterized them as both young men on the make. The Evansville Klavern became the most powerful in the state, and Stephenson soon contributed to attracting numerous new members. More than 5,400 men, or 23 percent of the native-born white men in [[Vanderburgh County, Indiana|Vanderburgh County]], ultimately joined the Klan.&lt;ref name="Moore"/&gt;

Building on the momentum, Stephenson set up a base in [[Indianapolis]], where he helped create the Klan's state newspaper, ''Fiery Cross''. He quickly recruited new agents and organizers, building on news about the organization. [[Protestantism|Protestant]] ministers were offered free membership. From July 1922 to July 1923, nearly 2,000 new members joined the Klan each week in Indiana.&lt;ref&gt;Moore (1997), ''Citizen Klansmen'', pp. 16–17&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hiram Wesley Evans]], who led recruiting for the national organization, maintained close ties to state leaders throughout 1921–1922 and he was especially close to Stephenson, because by then, Indiana had the largest state Klan organization. Stephenson backed Evans in November 1922 when he unseated [[William Joseph Simmons|William J. Simmons]] as [[Imperial Wizard]] of the national KKK. Evans had ambitions to make the Klan a political force in the country.

After Evans won, he officially appointed Stephenson as [[Grand Dragon]] of Indiana.  Privately he made him head of recruiting for seven other states north of [[Mississippi]]. In the 1920s, Klan membership grew dramatically in these states. In Indiana, membership grew to nearly 250,000 or about one third of all white males in the state. Stephenson acquired great wealth and political power by leading the Klan; agents received a portion of fees paid by new recruits, and he began to wield other powers.&lt;ref&gt;Rory McVeighn, "Structural incentives for conservative mobilization: Power devaluation and the rise of the Ku Klux Klan, 1915–1925" ''Social Forces'' (1999) 77#4 pp: 1461-1496.&lt;/ref&gt; Evans, who had a monopoly on the sale of Klan uniforms and paraphernalia, appointed Stephenson as Grand Dragon of the Indiana Klan at a 1923 [[Independence Day (United States)|Fourth of July]] gathering of the Klan in [[Kokomo, Indiana]], with more than 100,000 members and their families in attendance.&lt;ref&gt;Moore (1997), ''Citizen Klansmen'', pp. 17-19&lt;/ref&gt; Stephenson said,

&lt;blockquote&gt;My worthy subjects, citizens of the Invisible Empire, Klansmen all, greetings. It grieves me to be late. The President of the United States kept me unduly long counseling on matters of state. Only my plea that this is the time and the place of my coronation obtained for me surcease from his prayers for guidance.&lt;ref name="Lutholtz"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Encouraged by his success, in September 1923, Stephenson severed his ties with the existing national organization of the KKK, and formed a rival KKK that was made up of the chapters which he led. That year Stephenson changed his affiliation from the Democratic to [[History of the Republican Party (United States)|the Republican Party]], which was predominant in Indiana and much of the [[Midwestern United States|Midwest]]. He supported Republican [[Edward L. Jackson]], who was rumored to be a Klan member, when Jackson ran successfully for governor in 1924. Stephenson once claimed, "I am the law in Indiana."&lt;ref name="Lutholtz"/&gt; 

Shortly after, on May 12, 1924, at an assembly in the [[Cadle Tabernacle]] in Indianapolis, he said:&lt;blockquote&gt;"God help the man who issues a proclamation of war against the Klan in Indiana now ... We are going to Klux Indiana as she has never been Kluxed before ... I'll appeal to the ministers of Indiana to do the praying for the Ku Klux Klan and I'll do the scrapping for it ... And the fiery cross is going to burn at every crossroads in Indiana, as long as there is a white man left in the state."&lt;ref&gt;"Grand Dragon: D.C. Stephenson and the Ku Klux Klan in Indiana" by M. William Lutholtz. West Lafayette, Indiana, Purdue University Press, 1991, p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Convicted of murder==
Publicly a [[Prohibition|Prohibitionist]] and a defender of "[[Protestantism|Protestant]] womanhood," Stephenson was tried in 1925 for the rape and murder of [[Madge Oberholtzer]], a young state employee who ran a state program to combat adult illiteracy. During the trial, the Klan's image as upholders of law and morality were gravely weakened as it was proven that Stephenson and many of his associates were in private womanizers and alcoholics.&lt;ref name="Lutholtz"/&gt; The scandal of the charges and trial led to the rapid decline in  the "Second Wave" of Klan activity.&lt;ref name=vpappab&gt;[http://www.in.gov/library/2848.htm Ku Klux Klan in Indiana] Accessed December 16, 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Stephenson was convicted of the abduction, forced intoxication, and rape of Oberholtzer. His abuse led to her suicide attempt while she was still in his captivity. Because the suicide attempt eventually caused Oberholtzer's death, Stephenson was also charged with murder.

Stephenson had bitten her many times during his attack. The attending doctor described her condition as consisting of a significant bite on her breast.&lt;ref name=docsteph /&gt;  He later testified that the bite wounds that Stephenson inflicted on her were a leading contributor to her death due to a [[staph infection]] that eventually reached her lungs. The doctor also testified that she could have been saved if she had been given medical attention sooner.&lt;ref name=docsteph&gt;[http://law2.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/stephenson/atatevstprosecution.html STEPHENSON v. STATE: Testimony of Prosecution Witnesses (Excerpts) Oct. 29 -Nov. 4, 1925]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Stephenson Sentenced|work=Indianapolis News|pages=1|publisher=CHS 1920s Newspaper Project|date=1925-11-16|url=http://web.cathedral-irish.org/sites/teachers/thomas/newspaper/7th_period/front_page.htm|access-date=2008-01-13|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081210095414/http://web.cathedral-irish.org/sites/teachers/thomas/newspaper/7th_period/front_page.htm|archive-date=December 10, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In her dying declaration, Oberholtzer claimed that Stephenson had refused to give her medical attention unless she agreed to marry him first.&lt;ref name=made5232&gt;[http://law2.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/stephenson/dyingdeclaration.html The Dying Declaration Of Madge Oberholtzer: The Key Evidence In The 1925 Trial Of D. C. Stephenson, From ''My Indiana'' by Irving Liebowitz (1964) (pp.195-203)]&lt;/ref&gt;  The jury convicted Stephenson of second-degree murder on November 14, 1925, on its first ballot. Stephenson was sentenced to life in prison on November 16, 1925.&lt;ref name="Lutholtz"&gt;{{cite book|last=Lutholtz|first=M. William|title=Grand Dragon: D. C. Stephenson and the Ku Klux Klan in Indiana|publisher=Purdue University Press|year=1991|location=West Lafayette, Indiana|isbn=1-55753-046-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After his conviction, Governor [[Edward L. Jackson]] refused to grant Stephenson clemency or commute his sentence. On September 9, 1927, Stephenson released lists of public officials who were or had been on the Klan payroll. The ''[[Indianapolis Times]]'' interviewed Stephenson and proceeded with an extended investigation of the Klan's political ties.&lt;ref name="Center"/&gt; (The ''Times'' won a [[Pulitzer Prize for Public Service]] for its investigative reporting.&lt;ref name="Center"/&gt;) This publicity and the state's crackdown on Klan activity sped up the decline of the organization by the end of the 1920s. The KKK suffered a dramatic nationwide loss of reputation and its membership rapidly fell from 5 million in 1925; few Klan members were counted in the organization's former Midwestern stronghold soon after.

The state filed indictments against Governor Jackson; George V. "Cap" Coffin, chairman of the Marion County Republican Party; and attorney Robert I. Marsh, charging them with conspiring to bribe former Governor [[Warren McCray]]. The mayor of Indianapolis, [[John L. Duvall|John Duvall]], was convicted and sentenced to jail for 30 days (and barred from political service for four years). Some Republican commissioners of [[Marion County, Indiana|Marion County]] resigned from their posts after being charged with accepting bribes from the Klan and Stephenson.&lt;ref name="Center"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://centerforhistory.org/learn-history/indiana-history/the-golden-era-of-indiana-1900-1941|title=Indiana and the Ku Klux Klan|publisher=Center for History|url-status=dead|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150507171643/http://centerforhistory.org/learn-history/indiana-history/the-golden-era-of-indiana-1900-1941|archive-date=7 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years==
On January 7, 1941, the [[Valparaiso, Indiana|Valparaiso]] ''[[Vidette-Messenger]]'' reported that Governor [[M. Clifford Townsend]], a Democrat, was considering granting an early parole to Stephenson. No parole was approved that year. Stephenson was paroled on March 23, 1950, by a Democratic administration, but violated parole by disappearing on or before September 25, 1950. On December 15, 1950, he was captured in [[Minneapolis, Minnesota|Minneapolis]] and returned to custody. He was sentenced in 1951 to serve 10 years in prison. In 1953, he pleaded for release, denying that he had ever been a leader of the Klan. [[File:D.C. Stewphenson.jpg|thumb|right|180px|Grave marker located at USVA Mountain Home National Cemetery in Johnson City, Tennessee]] On December 22, 1956, the state paroled him, on condition that he leave Indiana and never return.&lt;ref name="Lutholtz"/&gt; Stephenson relocated to [[Seymour, Indiana]], where he soon married Martha Dickinson (they were separated less than a year later).

Stephenson then moved to [[Jonesborough, Tennessee]] (the town name was briefly spelled as "Jonesboro" during this time), where he was employed at the ''[[Herald &amp; Tribune]]'' newspaper,&lt;ref&gt;"Notre Dame Vs. the Klan: How the Fighting Irish Defeated the Ku Klux Klan". By Todd Tucker&lt;/ref&gt; and where he also married Martha Murray Sutton without having been divorced from Dickinson.

In 1961, at the age of 70, Stephenson was arrested in [[Independence, Missouri|Independence]], [[Missouri]], on charges of attempting to sexually assault a sixteen-year-old girl but he was later released after paying a $300 fine because the charges were dropped on grounds of insufficient evidence. He was ordered to leave Missouri immediately. &lt;ref name="Lutholtz"/&gt; A few years later, in 1966, Stephenson died at his home in [[Jonesborough, Tennessee]], and he was buried at the [[Mountain Home National Cemetery|USVA Mountain Home National Cemetery]] in [[Johnson City, Tennessee]].

==Cultural references==
*[[John Heard (actor)|John Heard]] portrayed Stephenson in the television miniseries ''[[Cross of Fire]]'' (1989).  
*In [[Daniel Easterman]]'s alternate history [[novel]] ''[[K is for Killing]]'' (1997), Stephenson is featured as the sinister power behind the throne after the [[isolationism|isolationist]] Senator [[Charles Lindbergh]] is elected [[President of the United States]]. Easterman reflected the documented predatory sexual behavior of Stephenson in the novel. He was portrayed as a politically savvy but unstable ally of [[Adolf Hitler]].&lt;ref&gt;Easterman, Daniel. ''K is for Killing'', London, England: HarperCollinsPublishers, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Indiana Klan]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Lutholtz, M. William. ''Grand Dragon: DC Stephenson and the Ku Klux Klan in Indiana'' (Purdue University Press, 1991).
* Moore, Leonard J. ''Citizen Klansmen: The Ku Klux Klan in Indiana, 1921-1928'' (University of North Carolina Press, 1997).
* Smith, Ron F. ''"The Klan's Retribution Against an Indiana Editor: A Reconsideration."'' Indiana Magazine of History 106#4 (2010): 381-400.
* Leibowitz, Irving. ''"My Indiana"'' (Prentice Hall Inc., 1964)

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20150507171643/http://centerforhistory.org/learn-history/indiana-history/the-golden-era-of-indiana-1900-1941 "Indiana and the Ku Klux Klan"], Center for History 
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080130134128/http://www.columbia.edu/~rr91/1402-2007/The%20Stephenson%20Trial%20prospectus.htm Lindsay Dunn, ''The Stephenson Trial: Internal Klan Conflicts Linked to Downfall of Second Klan in Indiana''], Columbia University 
*[https://www.indianahistory.org/wp-content/uploads/d-c-stephenson-collection-1922-1978.pdf "D.C. Stephenson Collection, 1922-1978" Collection Guide], [[Indiana Historical Society]], accessed 2012-10-19. 
*[http://law2.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/stephenson/stephensonhome.html "D. C. Stephenson Trial (1925)"] Doug Linder, 2010. University of Missouri-Kansas City (UMKC) School of Law.
*[https://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/murder-wasnt-very-pretty-the-rise-and-fall-of-dc-stephenson-18935042/ ""Murder Wasn’t Very Pretty": The Rise and Fall of D.C. Stephenson"] Karen Abbott. smithsonian.com, August 30, 2012. Retrieved November 21, 2017.

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stephenson, D. C.}}
[[Category:1891 births]]
[[Category:1966 deaths]]
[[Category:American people convicted of kidnapping]]
[[Category:American people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:American people convicted of rape]]
[[Category:American prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment]]
[[Category:Crimes in Indiana]]
[[Category:Indiana Democrats]]
[[Category:Indiana politicians convicted of crimes]]
[[Category:Ku Klux Klan Grand Dragons]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Indiana]]
[[Category:People from Houston]]
[[Category:People from Maysville, Oklahoma]]
[[Category:People paroled from life sentence]]
[[Category:Politicians convicted of murder]]
[[Category:Politicians convicted of sex offences]]
[[Category:Prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment by Indiana]]
[[Category:Indiana Republicans]]
[[Category:People from Jonesborough, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Child sexual abuse in the United States]]
[[Category:1925 murders in the United States]]
[[Category: State and local political sex scandals in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>ikp4vh600skugw00kqb9r7woowlk7mr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
