<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Amelia Dyer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11443817</id>
    <revision>
      <id>944341990</id>
      <parentid>944341879</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-07T06:48:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>79.75.111.82</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Jack the Ripper speculation */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="27761" xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=January 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{{more citations needed|date=March 2017}}
{{Infobox serial killer
| name=Amelia Dyer
| image=Amelia dyer1893.jpg
| caption=Amelia Dyer
| birth_name=Amelia Elizabeth Hobley
| alias=The Reading Baby Farmer, Mrs. Thomas
| birth_date=1836
| birth_place=Pyle Marsh, [[Bristol]], [[England]], [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]
| death_date=10 June 1896 (aged 59/60)
| death_place=[[Newgate Prison]], [[London]], England, United Kingdom
| spouse=George Thomas&lt;br&gt;William Dyer
| cause=State execution by [[hanging]]
| penalty=Death
| victims=200-400+ attributed; 6 confirmed
| country=England, United Kingdom
| states=
| motive=Financial gain
| apprehended=3 April 1896
| children=Ellen Thomas, Mary Ann "Polly" Dyer, William Samuel Dyer
|endyear=1896|beginyear=1880}}

'''Amelia Elizabeth Dyer''' (née '''Hobley'''; 1836 – 10 June 1896) was one of the most prolific [[serial killer]]s in history, [[murder]]ing infants in her care over a 30-year period in [[Victorian era|Victorian Britain]].&lt;ref name="tragedy"&gt;[http://www.capitalpunishmentuk.org/babyfarm.html "'Baby Farming' – a tragedy of Victorian times."]. Retrieved 2008-10-28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=alison/&gt; Trained as a nurse, and widowed in 1869, she turned to [[baby farming]]—the practice of adopting unwanted infants in exchange for money—to support herself. She initially cared for the children legitimately, in addition to having two of her own, but whether intentionally or not, a number of them died in her care, leading to a conviction for negligence and six months' hard labour. She then began directly murdering children she "adopted", strangling at least some of them, and disposing of the bodies to avoid attention. Mentally unstable, she was committed to several [[mental asylum]]s throughout her life, despite suspicions of [[feigning]], and survived at least one serious suicide attempt.

Dyer's downfall came when the bagged corpse of an infant was discovered in the [[Thames]], with evidence leading to her. She was arrested on 4 April 1896, tried for the murder of infant Doris Marmon, and hanged on 10 June 1896. At the time of her death, a handful of murders were attributed to her, but there is little doubt she was responsible for many more similar deaths—possibly 400 or more.&lt;ref name="cole"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Thames Valley Police Museum"&gt;{{cite web|title=The Baby Farmer|url=http://www.thamesvalley.police.uk/aboutus-museum-baby-farmer|publisher=Thames Valley Police|accessdate=17 October 2015|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160302213715/http://www.thamesvalley.police.uk/aboutus-museum-baby-farmer|archivedate=2 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-berkshire-39330793|title=Amelia Dyer: The Victorian nurse who strangled babies|date=3 June 2017|website=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dubbed the "Ogress of Reading", she inspired a popular ballad, and her case led to stricter laws for adoption.

==Background==
Amelia Dyer was born the youngest of five (with three brothers, Thomas, James and William, and a sister, Ann) in the small village of Pyle Marsh,&lt;ref name=alison&gt;Vale, Allison; Alison Rattle (2007). ''Amelia Dyer: Angel Maker'', {{ISBN|978-0-233-00224-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; just east of [[Bristol]] (now part of Bristol's [[urban sprawl]] known as Pile Marsh), the daughter of a master [[shoemaker]], Samuel Hobley, and Sarah Hobley née Weymouth. She learned to read and write and developed a love of literature and poetry.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/femail/article-484575/The-baby-butcher-One-Victorian-Britains-evil-murderers-exposed.html |newspaper=Daily Mail |title=The baby butcher: One of Victorian Britain's most evil murderers exposed |accessdate=2008-10-21 | date=28 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, her childhood was marred by the mental illness of her mother, caused by [[typhus]]. Amelia witnessed her mother's violent fits and was obliged to care for her until she died, raving, in 1848. Researchers later commented on the effect this had on Dyer, and also what it taught her about the symptoms exhibited by those who appear to lose their mind through illness.&lt;ref name="cole"&gt;''The Lady Killers'' (1998). Amelia Dyer, ITV series. Hosted by Martina Cole. Broadcast 2010-03-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dyer had an elder sister, Sarah Ann who died in 1841, aged 6 and a younger sister also named Sarah Ann who died in 1845, aged a few months. An elder cousin had an illegitimate daughter at the time who was later accepted as the daughter of the grandparents, Dyer's aunt and uncle William and Martha Hobley.

After her mother's death Amelia lived with an aunt in Bristol for a while, before serving an apprenticeship with a corset maker. Her father died in 1859. Her eldest brother, Thomas, inherited the family shoe business. In 1861, at the age of 24, Amelia became permanently estranged from at least one of her brothers, James, and moved into lodgings in Trinity Street, Bristol.&lt;ref name=alison/&gt; There she married George Thomas. George was 59 and they both lied about their ages on the marriage certificate to reduce the age gap. George deducted 11 years from his age and Amelia added 6 years to her age&lt;ref name=alison/&gt;—many sources later reported this age as fact, causing much confusion.

==Nursing==
After marrying George Thomas, Dyer trained as a [[nurse]]. From contact with a [[midwife]], Ellen Dane, she learned of an easier way to earn a living—using her own home to provide lodgings for young women who had conceived [[Legitimacy (family law)|illegitimately]] and then farming off the babies for adoption or allowing them to die of neglect and malnutrition. (Ellen Dane was forced to decamp to the US, shortly after meeting Amelia, to escape the attention of the authorities.)&lt;ref name=alison/&gt; Unmarried mothers in Victorian Britain often struggled to gain an income, since the 1834 [[Poor Law Amendment Act]] had removed any financial obligation from the fathers of illegitimate children, whilst bringing up their children in a society where single parenthood and illegitimacy were stigmatized. This led to the practice of [[baby farming]] in which individuals acted as [[adoption]] or [[foster care|fostering]] agents, in return for regular payments or a single, up-front fee from the babies' mothers. Many businesses were set up to take in these young women and care for them until they gave birth. The mothers subsequently left their unwanted babies to be looked after as "nurse children".&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

The predicament of the parents involved was often exploited for financial gain: if a baby had well-off parents who were simply anxious to keep the birth secret, the single fee might be as much as £80. Fifty pounds might be negotiated if the father of the child wanted to hush up his involvement. However, it was more common for these expectant young women to be impoverished. Such women would be charged about £5.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

Unscrupulous carers resorted to [[Starvation|starving]] the farmed-out babies, to save money and even to hasten death. Noisy or demanding babies could be sedated with easily available alcohol and/or [[opiate]]s. [[Godfrey's Cordial]]—known colloquially as "Mother's Friend", (a syrup containing [[opium]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://pediatrics.aappublications.org/cgi/content/abstract/45/6/1011 "What Were Godfrey's Cordial And Dalby's Carminative?, ''Pediatrics''.] Retrieved 2008-10-23&lt;/ref&gt;—was a frequent choice, but there were several other similar preparations.&lt;ref name="opium"/&gt; Many children died as a result of such dubious practices: "Opium killed far more infants through starvation than directly through [[Drug overdose|overdose]]." Dr. Greenhow, investigating for the [[Privy council|Privy Council]], noted how children "kept in a state of continued [[Unconsciousness|narcotism]] will be thereby disinclined for food, and be but imperfectly nourished." Death from severe [[malnutrition]] would result, but the [[coroner]] was likely to record the death as {{"'}}debility from birth,' or 'lack of breast milk,' or simply 'starvation. {{'"}}&lt;ref name="opium"&gt;Quoted in: [http://www.victorianweb.org/science/health/health4.html ''Opium and Infant Mortality''] Retrieved 2008-10-24, sourced from Wohl, Anthony S. ''Endangered Lives: Public Health in Victorian Britain.'' Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1983. pp. 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt; Mothers who chose to reclaim or simply check on the welfare of their children could often encounter difficulties, but some would simply be too frightened or ashamed to tell the police about any suspected wrongdoing. Even the authorities often had problems tracing any children that were reported missing.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

This was the world opened up to her by the now-departed Ellen Dane. Dyer had to leave nursing with the birth of a daughter, Ellen Thomas. In 1869 the elderly George Thomas died and Amelia needed an income.&lt;ref name=alison/&gt;

==Murders==
Dyer was keen to make money from baby farming, and alongside taking in expectant women, she advertised to [[breastfeeding|nurse]] and adopt a baby, in return for a substantial one-off payment and adequate clothing for the child. In her advertisements and meetings with clients, she assured them that she was respectable and married and that she would provide a safe and loving home for the child.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

In 1872, Amelia married William Dyer, a brewer's laborer from Bristol.&lt;ref&gt;Register of Marriages for Bristol Registration District, Volume 6a (1872) p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; They had two children together: Mary Ann, also known as Polly, and William Samuel. Amelia eventually left her husband.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Hobley-10&lt;/ref&gt;

At some point in her baby farming career, Dyer decided to forgo the expense and inconvenience of letting the children die through neglect and starvation; soon after the receipt of each child, she murdered them, thus allowing her to pocket most or all of the fee.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

For some time, Dyer eluded the resulting interest of the police. She was eventually caught in 1879 after a doctor was suspicious about the number of child deaths he had been called to certify in Dyer's care. However, instead of being convicted of murder or [[manslaughter]], she was sentenced to six months' hard labor for [[Neglect (English law)|neglect]]. The experience allegedly almost destroyed her mentally,&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt; though others have expressed incredulity at the leniency of the sentence when compared to those handed out for lesser crimes at that time.

Upon release, she attempted to resume her nursing career. She had spells in [[mental hospital]]s due to her alleged mental instability and suicidal tendencies;&lt;ref name="Rose, Lionel 1986 p.160"&gt;Rose, Lionel (1986). ''The Massacre of the Innocents'', Routledge, p.160&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rose, Lionel (1986). ''The Massacre of the Innocents'', Routledge. [https://books.google.com/books?id=sZc9AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PP7] Retrieved 2008-10-24&lt;/ref&gt; these always coincided with times when it was convenient for her to "disappear". Being a former asylum nurse Dyer knew how to behave to ensure a relatively comfortable existence as an asylum inmate.&lt;ref name=alison/&gt; Dyer appears to have begun abusing alcohol and opium-based products early in her killing career; her mental instability could have been related to her substance abuse. In 1890, Dyer cared for the illegitimate baby of a governess. When she returned to visit the child, the governess was immediately suspicious and stripped the baby to see if a birthmark was present on one of its hips. It wasn't, and prolonged suspicions by the authorities led to Dyer having or feigning, a breakdown. Dyer at one point drank two bottles of [[laudanum]] in a serious suicide attempt, but her long-term abuse had built up her tolerance to opium products, so she survived.

She returned to baby farming and murder. Dyer realized the folly of involving doctors to issue [[death certificate]]s and began disposing of the bodies herself. The precarious nature and extent of her activities again prompted undesirable attention; she was alert to the attention of police—and of parents seeking to reclaim their children. She and her family frequently relocated to different towns and cities to escape suspicion, regain anonymity—and to acquire new business. Over the years, Dyer used a succession of aliases.&lt;ref name="Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Rose, Lionel 1986 p.160"/&gt;

In 1893, Dyer was discharged from her final committal at the [[Mendip Hospital|Somerset and Bath Lunatic Asylum]] near Wells.&lt;ref name="Rose, Lionel 1986 p.160"/&gt; Unlike previous "breakdowns" this had been a most disagreeable experience, and she never entered another asylum.&lt;ref name=alison/&gt; Two years later, Dyer moved to [[Caversham, Reading|Caversham]], Berkshire, accompanied by an unsuspecting associate, Jane "Granny" Smith, whom Dyer had recruited from a brief spell in a workhouse and Dyer's daughter and son-in-law, Mary Ann (known as Polly) and Arthur Palmer. This was followed by a move to 45 Kensington Road, [[Reading, Berkshire]] later the same year.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt; Smith was persuaded by Dyer to be referred to as 'mother' in front of innocent women handing over their children. This was an effort to present a caring mother-daughter image.

===Case study: the murder of Doris Marmon===
In January 1896, Evelina Marmon, a popular 25-year-old barmaid, gave birth to an illegitimate daughter, Doris, in a boarding house in [[Cheltenham]]. She quickly sought offers of adoption and placed an advertisement in the "Miscellaneous" section of the ''Bristol Times &amp; Mirror'' newspaper. It simply read: "Wanted, respectable woman to take a young child." Marmon intended to go back to work and hoped to eventually reclaim her child.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

Coincidentally, next to her own, was an advertisement reading: "Married couple with no family would adopt a healthy child, nice country home. Terms, £10". Marmon responded, to a "Mrs. Harding", and a few days later she received a reply from Dyer. From Oxford Road in Reading, "Mrs. Harding" wrote that "I should be glad to have a dear baby girl, one I could bring up and call my own." She continued: "We are plain, homely people, in fairly good circumstances. I don't want a child for money's sake, but the company and home comfort&amp;nbsp;... I and my husband are dearly fond of children. I have no child of my own. A child with me will have a good home and a mother's love".&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

Evelina Marmon wanted to pay a more affordable, weekly fee for the care of her daughter, but "Mrs. Harding" insisted on being given the one-off payment in advance. Marmon was in dire straits, so she reluctantly agreed to pay the £10, and a week later "Mrs. Harding" arrived in Cheltenham.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

Marmon was surprised by Dyer's advanced age and stocky appearance, but as Dyer was affectionate towards Doris, Evelina handed over her daughter, a cardboard box of clothes and £10. Still distressed at having to give up care for her daughter, Evelina accompanied Dyer to Cheltenham station, and then on to [[Gloucester]]. She returned to her lodgings "a broken woman". A few days later, she received a letter from "Mrs. Harding" saying all was well; Marmon wrote back, but received no reply.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

Dyer did not travel to Reading, as she had told Marmon. She went instead to 76 Mayo Road, [[Willesden]], London where her 23-year-old daughter Polly was staying. There, Dyer quickly found some white edging tape used in [[Dressmaker|dressmaking]], wound it twice around the baby's neck and tied a knot. Death would not have been immediate.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt; Dyer later said: "I used to like to watch them with the tape around their neck, but it was soon all over with them."&lt;ref name=alison/&gt;

Both women allegedly helped to wrap the body in a napkin. They kept some of the clothes Marmon had packed; the rest was destined for the [[pawnbroker]]. Dyer paid the rent to the unwitting landlady and gave her a pair of child's boots as a present for her little girl. The following day, Wednesday 1 April 1896, another child, named Harry Simmons, was taken to Mayo Road. However, with no spare white edging tape available, the length around Doris's corpse was removed and used to strangle the 13-month-old boy.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

On 2 April, both bodies were stacked into a [[carpet bag]], along with bricks for added weight. Dyer then headed for Reading. At a secluded spot, she knew well near a weir at [[Caversham Lock]], she forced the carpetbag through railings into the [[River Thames]].&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

==Dyer's downfall==

===Discovery of corpses===
Unbeknownst to Dyer, on 30 March 1896, a package was retrieved from the Thames at Reading by a [[barge]]man. The package Dyer dumped was not weighted adequately and had been easily spotted. It contained the body of a baby girl, later identified as Helena Fry. In the small detective force available to [[Reading Borough Police]], Detective [[Constable]] Anderson made a crucial breakthrough. As well as finding a label from [[Bristol Temple Meads railway station|Temple Meads station]], Bristol, he used microscopic analysis of the wrapping paper and deciphered a faintly legible name—Mrs. Thomas—and an address.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

This evidence was enough to lead police to Dyer, but they still had no strong evidence to connect her directly with a serious crime. Additional evidence they gleaned from witnesses, and information obtained from Bristol police, only served to increase their concerns, and D.C. Anderson, with [[Sgt.]] James placed Dyer's home under surveillance. Subsequent intelligence suggested that Dyer would abscond if she came at all under suspicion. The officers decided to use a young woman as a decoy, hoping she would be able to secure a meeting with Dyer to discuss her services. This may have been designed to help the detectives to positively link Dyer to her business activities, or it may have simply given them a reliable opportunity to arrest her.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

It transpired that Dyer was expecting her new client (the decoy) to call, but instead, she found detectives waiting on her doorstep. On 3 April (Good Friday), the police raided her home. They were struck by the stench of human decomposition, although no human remains were found. There was, however, plenty of other related evidence, including white edging tape, [[telegram]]s regarding adoption arrangements, [[pawn ticket]]s for children's clothing, receipts for advertisements and letters from mothers inquiring about the well-being of their children.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

The police calculated that in the previous few months alone, at least twenty children had been placed in the care of a "Mrs. Thomas", now revealed to be Amelia Dyer. It also appeared that she was about to move home again, this time to [[Somerset]].&lt;ref name="Thebabybutcher"/&gt; This rate of murder has led to some estimates that Mrs. Dyer may, over decades, have killed over 400 babies and children, making her one of the most prolific murderers ever.&lt;ref name="cole"/&gt;

Dyer was arrested on 4 April and charged with murder. Her son-in-law Arthur Palmer was charged as an [[Accessory (legal term)|accessory]]. During April, the Thames was dredged and six more bodies were discovered, including Doris Marmon and Harry Simmons—Dyer's last victims. Each baby had been strangled with white tape, which as she later told the police "was how you could tell it was one of mine".&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;
Eleven days after handing her daughter to Dyer, Evelina Marmon, whose name had emerged in items kept by Dyer, identified her daughter's remains.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

===Inquest and trial===
[[File:amelia-dyer.jpg|320px|thumb|right|Police photo of Dyer after her arrest in 1896]]
At the inquest into the deaths in early May, no evidence was found that Mary Ann or Arthur Palmer had acted as Dyer's accomplices. Arthur Palmer was discharged as the result of a confession written by Amelia Dyer. In Reading Gaol she wrote (with her spelling and punctuation preserved):

{{quote|Sir will you kindly grant me the favor of presenting this to the [[magistrate]]s on Saturday the 18th instant I have made this statement out, for I may not have the opportunity then I must relieve my mind I do know and I feel my days are numbered on this earth but I do feel it is an awful thing drawing innocent people into trouble I do know I should have to answer before my Maker in Heaven for the awful crimes I have committed but as God Almighty is my judge in Heaven an on Hearth neither my daughter Mary Ann Palmer nor her husband Alfred Ernest Palmer I do most solemnly declare neither of them had anything at all to do with it, they never knew I contemplated doing such a wicked thing until it was too late I am speaking the truth and nothing but the truth as I hope to be forgiven, I and I alone must stand before my Maker in Heaven to answer it all witness my hand Amelia Dyer. |April 16, 1896, &lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;}}

On 22 May 1896, Dyer appeared at the [[Old Bailey]] and pleaded guilty to one murder, that of Doris Marmon. Her family and associates testified at her trial that they had been growing suspicious and uneasy about her activities, and it emerged that Dyer had narrowly escaped discovery on several occasions.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt; Evidence from a man who had seen and spoken to Dyer when she had disposed of the two bodies at Caversham Lock also proved significant. Her daughter had given graphic evidence that ensured Dyer's conviction.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

The only defense Dyer offered was [[insanity defense|insanity]]: she had been twice committed to asylums in Bristol. However, the prosecution argued successfully that her exhibitions of mental instability had been a ploy to avoid suspicion; both committals were said to have coincided with times when Dyer was concerned her crimes might have been exposed.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

It took the jury only four and a half minutes to find her guilty. In her three weeks in the condemned cell, she filled five exercise books with her "last true and only confession". Visited the night before her execution by the chaplain and asked if she had anything to confess, she offered him her exercise books, saying, "isn't this enough?"&lt;ref name="tragedy"/&gt; Curiously, she was subpoenaed to appear as a witness in Polly's trial for murder, set for a week after her execution date. However, it was ruled that Dyer was already legally dead once sentenced and that therefore her evidence would be inadmissible. Thus, her execution was not delayed. On the eve of her execution, Dyer heard that the charges against Polly had been dropped. Dyer was hanged by [[James Billington (executioner)|James Billington]] at [[Newgate Prison]] on Wednesday, 10 June 1896.&lt;ref name="Rose, Lionel 1986 p.161"&gt;{{cite book | last = Rose | first = Lionel | year = 1986 | title = Massacre of the Innocents: Infanticide in Britain, 1800-1939 | publisher = Routledge | page = 161}}&lt;/ref&gt; Asked on the scaffold if she had anything to say, she said "I have nothing to say", just before being dropped at 9&amp;nbsp;a.m. precisely.

==Later developments==
It is uncertain how many more children Amelia Dyer murdered. However, inquiries from mothers, evidence of other witnesses, and material found in Dyer's homes, including letters and many babies' clothes, pointed to many more.&lt;ref name=" Thames Valley Police Museum"/&gt;

The Dyer case caused a scandal. She became known as the "Ogress of Reading", and she inspired a popular ballad:

{{quote|The old baby farmer, the wretched Miss Dyer&lt;br/&gt;At the Old Bailey her wages is paid.&lt;br/&gt;In times long ago, we'd 'a' made a big fy-er&lt;br/&gt;And roasted so nicely that wicked old jade.&lt;ref name="Rose, Lionel 1986 p.161"/&gt;}}

Adoption laws were subsequently made stricter, giving local authorities the power to police baby farms in the hope of stamping out abuse. Despite this and the scrutinizing of newspaper personal ads,&lt;ref name="Rose, Lionel 1986 p.161"/&gt; the trafficking and abuse of infants did not stop. Two years after Dyer's execution, railway workers inspecting carriages at [[Newton Abbot]], [[Devon]], found a parcel. Inside was a three-week-old girl but, though cold and wet, she was alive. The daughter of a widow, Jane Hill, the baby had been given to Mrs. Stewart, for £12. She had picked up the baby at [[Plymouth]]—and dumped her on the next train. It has been claimed that "Mrs. Stewart" was Polly, the daughter of Amelia Dyer.&lt;ref name=Thebabybutcher/&gt;

The character of Amelia Dyer appeared in the short story "The Baby Farmer" by Philip Fracassi in his horror collection ''Behold the Void''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Fracassi |first1=Philip |title=Behold the Void |date=2018 |publisher=Lovecraft eZine Press |isbn=9780578423692 |pages=97–120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Identified victims==
*Doris Marmon, 4 months old
*Harry Simmons, 13 months old
*Helena Fry, age unknown, 1-year-old or younger

==Jack the Ripper speculation==
Because she was a murderess alive at the time of the [[Jack the Ripper]] killings, some have suggested that Dyer was Jack the Ripper, who killed the prostitutes through botched abortions.{{Citation needed|reason=This is stated as a known fact, but I cannot turn up conclusive links to botched-abortions-as-Ripper-methodology|date=November 2019}} This suggestion was put forward by author William Stewart, although he preferred [[Mary Pearcey]] as his chosen suspect.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |first=William |last=Stewart |year=1939 |title=Jack The Ripper: A New Theory |publisher=Quality Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is, however, no evidence to connect Dyer to the Jack the Ripper murders.

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==See also==
{{commons}}
*[[Amelia Sach and Annie Walters]]
*[[Dagmar Overbye]]
*[[John and Sarah Makin]]
*[[Minnie Dean]]
*[[Frances Knorr]]
*[[Capital punishment in the United Kingdom]]
*[[Infanticide in 19th-century New Zealand]] kasvfounvb isjv isdv isuvrhg iwrj 

==References==
* [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/femail/article-484575/The-baby-butcher-One-Victorian-Britains-evil-murderers-exposed.html ''Daily Mail'', "The baby butcher: One of Victorian Britain's most evil murderers exposed".] (Review of Vale &amp; Rattle biography ''Amelia Dyer: Angel Maker'').
* Rose, Lionel (1986). ''The Massacre of the Innocents'', Routledge, p.&amp;nbsp;160 {{ISBN|978-0-7102-0339-7}}
* [http://www.capitalpunishmentuk.org/babyfarm.html "'Baby Farming' – a tragedy of Victorian times."].
* Vale, Allison; Alison Rattle (2007). ''Amelia Dyer: Angel Maker''. Andre Deutsch. {{ISBN|978-0-233-00224-8}}
* James, Mike (ed.) (1994). ''Bedside Book of Murder'' Forum Press / True Crime Library. {{ISBN|1-874358-07-9}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dyer, Amelia}}
[[Category:1837 births]]
[[Category:1896 deaths]]
[[Category:1879 crimes]]
[[Category:19th-century executions by England and Wales]]
[[Category: British female serial killers]]
[[Category: English murderers of children]]
[[Category: English people convicted of murder]]
[[Category: English serial killers]]
[[Category: Executed English women]]
[[Category: Executed people from Bristol]]
[[Category: Executed serial killers]]
[[Category: Nurses convicted of killing patients]]
[[Category: Women of the Victorian era]]
[[Category:Infanticide]]
[[Category:1870s murders in the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>22wx4slzrrynuw00qdknf8xz1649v9w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
