<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Daniel Camargo Barbosa</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1326084</id>
    <revision>
      <id>938165771</id>
      <parentid>938165729</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-01-29T14:36:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MilfordBoy1991</username>
        <id>16899599</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Escape from Colombia to Ecuador */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="12122" xml:space="preserve">{{Spanish name|Camargo|Barbosa}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{refimprove|date=March 2017}}
{{Infobox serial killer
| name = Daniel Camargo Barbosa
| image =
| caption =
| birthname = Daniel Camargo Barbosa
| alias = Manuel Bulgarin Solis
| birth_date = {{birth date|df=y|1930|1|22}}
| birth_place = [[Anolaima]], [[Cundinamarca Department|Cundinamarca]], [[Colombia]]
| death_date = {{death date and age|df=y|1994|11|13|1930|1|22}}
| death_place = [[Guayaquil]], [[Ecuador]]
| cause = Retaliatory murder
| victims = 72–150
| country = [[Colombia]], [[Ecuador]]
| states = [[Guayas Province|Guayas]], [[Pichincha Province|Pichincha]], [[Tungurahua Province|Tungurahua]], [[El Oro Province|El Oro]], [[Los Rios Province|Los Rios]]
| beginyear = 1974
| endyear = 1986
| apprehended = 3 May 1974; escaped November 1984; re-apprehended 26 February 1986
| penalty = 25-year sentence, 16-year sentence
}}
'''Daniel Camargo Barbosa''' (22 January 1930 – 13 November 1994) was a [[Colombian people|Colombian]] [[serial killer]]. It is believed that he [[raped]] and murdered up to 150 young girls in [[Colombia]] and [[Ecuador]] during the 1970s and 1980s.

==Early life==
Camargo's mother died when he was a little boy and his father was overbearing and emotionally distant. He was raised by an abusive stepmother, who punished him and sometimes dressed him in girls' clothing, making him a victim of ridicule in front of his peers.&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity"&gt;{{cite news|title=La Infancia y La Virginidad: Dos Vertientes Del Crimen|newspaper=Hoy|date=15 November 1994|accessdate=31 March 2010|location=Ecuador|language=Spanish|trans-title=Children and Virginity: Twofold Crime|url=http://www.explored.com.ec/noticias-ecuador/la-infancia-y-la-virginidad-dos-vertientes-del-crimen-26963-26963.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110125153025/http://www.explored.com.ec/noticias-ecuador/la-infancia-y-la-virginidad-dos-vertientes-del-crimen-26963-26963.html|archive-date=25 January 2011|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Crimes and imprisonment==
He was first arrested in [[Bogotá]] on 24 May 1958 for [[petty theft]].&lt;ref name="Timeline"&gt;{{cite news |title=Cronologia de los Asesinatos de Camargo Barbosa |newspaper=Hoy |date=15 November 1994 |accessdate=31 March 2010 |location=Ecuador |language=Spanish |trans-title=Timeline of the Murders of Barbosa Camargo |url=http://www.hoy.com.ec/noticias-ecuador/cronologia-de-los-asesinatos-de-camargo-barbosa-26954-26954.html |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100529160106/http://www.hoy.com.ec/noticias-ecuador/cronologia-de-los-asesinatos-de-camargo-barbosa-26954-26954.html |archivedate=29 May 2010 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Camargo had a [[Common-law marriage|de facto union]] with a woman named Alcira and had two children with her. He fell in love with another woman, Esperanza (age 28), whom he planned to marry, but then found out that she was not a [[virgin]]. This became the root of Camargo's fixations. He and Esperanza formed an agreement that he would stay with her if she aided him in finding other virgin girls to have sex with. This began a period of their partnership in crime. Esperanza was Camargo's accomplice, luring young girls to an apartment under false pretenses and then drugging them with [[Secobarbital|sodium seconal]] [[Hypnotic|sleeping pills]] so that Camargo could [[rape]] them. Camargo committed five rapes in this way, but did not kill any of the girls. The fifth child that they abused in this way reported the crime, and both Camargo and Esperanza were arrested and taken to separate prisons.&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity" /&gt; Camargo was convicted of sexual assault in Colombia on 10 April 1964.&lt;ref name="Sadistic"&gt;{{cite news|title='El sádico del Chanquito'|author=Special Envoy Jose Comas|newspaper=El Pais|date=2 February 1988|accessdate=31 March 2010|location=Spain|language=Spanish|trans-title=The Chanquito sadistic|url=http://www.elpais.com/articulo/internacional/COLOMBIA/ECUADOR/sadico/Chanquito/elpepiint/19880207elpepiint_5/Tes/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A judge sentenced Camargo to three years in prison, and Camargo was initially grateful for the perceived leniency of the judge, swearing to repent and mend his ways. However, a new judge was given precedence over the case and Camargo was sentenced to eight years in prison. This provoked Camargo to rebellious anger. He served his full sentence, and was then released.&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity" /&gt;

In 1973 he was arrested in [[Brazil]] for being [[Undocumented immigrant|undocumented]]. Due to a delay in sending Camargo's criminal records from Colombia, he was [[deported]] and released with his false identity.&lt;ref name="Timeline" /&gt; When he returned to Colombia, he took up a job as a street vendor in [[Barranquilla]] selling [[Video monitor|television monitors]]. One day when passing by a school, he kidnapped a 9-year-old girl, after raping her, he murdered her so that she could not inform the police as his previous victim had done. This was his first assault involving murder.&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Sadistic" /&gt;

Camargo was arrested on 3 May 1974 in Barranquilla, Colombia, when he returned to the scene of the crime to recover the television screens that he had left beside the victim. Even though it is believed that he raped and killed more than 80 girls in Colombia, Camargo was imprisoned in Colombia after being convicted of raping and killing a 9-year-old girl. He was initially sentenced to 30 years in prison, but this sentence was reduced to 25 years, and he was interned in the prison on the island of [[Gorgona, Colombia]]&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity" /&gt; on 24 December 1977.&lt;ref name="Sadistic" /&gt;

==Escape from Colombia to Ecuador==
In November 1984 Camargo escaped from Gorgona prison (known as the Colombian [[Alcatraz Island|Alcatraz]]) in a primitive boat after having carefully studied the [[ocean currents]]. The authorities assumed that he died at sea and the press reported that he had been eaten by [[shark]]s.&lt;ref name="Sadistic" /&gt; He eventually arrived in [[Quito]], Ecuador. He then traveled by bus to [[Guayaquil]] on 5 or 6 December 1984.&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity" /&gt; On 18 December he abducted a 9-year-old girl from the city of [[Quevedo, Ecuador|Quevedo]], in the province of [[Los Ríos Province|Los Ríos]], Ecuador. The next day a 10-year-old girl also disappeared.

From 1984 to 1986 Camargo committed a series of at least 54 rapes and murders in Guayaquil. The police at first believed that all the deaths were the work of a gang, not understanding that one man could have killed so many. Camargo slept on the streets, and lived off of the money he could gain by reselling ballpoint pens in the streets. Occasionally he supplemented his income by selling clothing or small valuables belonging to his victims.&lt;ref name="Sadistic" /&gt;

==Modus operandi==
Camargo selected helpless, young, lower-class girls in search of work and approached them, pretending to be a foreigner who needed to find a Protestant pastor in a church on the outskirts of town. He explained that he had to deliver a large sum of money, which he showed them as proof, and he offered them a reward if they would accompany him to show him the way. He pretended that he was a stranger to the area, and hinted at the possibility of the girls getting a job at the factory. No one was suspicious of an older man accompanying a girl or young woman who could be his granddaughter. Camargo would then enter into the woods, claiming to be looking for a shortcut in order to avoid arousing suspicion in his victims. If the girls did grow suspicious and drew back, he did not prevent them from leaving. Camargo raped his victims before strangling them, sometimes stabbing them when they resisted. After his victims were dead, he left their bodies in the forest to be picked clean by [[scavenger]]s.&lt;ref name="Sadistic" /&gt;

==Arrest==
Camargo was arrested by two policemen in Quito on 26 February 1986, only a few minutes after he had murdered a 9-year-old girl named Elizabeth. The policemen were on patrol and approached him at the height of the avenue Los Granados, thinking that he was acting suspiciously. They found that he was carrying with him a bag containing the bloody clothes and clitoris of his latest victim, and a copy of ''[[Crime and Punishment]]'' by [[Dostoyevsky]].&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity"/&gt; He was taken into custody and later moved to Guayaquil for identification. When he was arrested he gave a false name, Manuel Bulgarin Solis, but he was later identified by one of his rape victims who escaped.&lt;ref name="Timeline" /&gt;

Daniel Camargo calmly confessed to killing 72 girls in [[Ecuador]] since escaping from the Colombian prison. He led authorities to the dumping grounds of those victims whose bodies had not yet been recovered. The bodies had been dismembered. While he told the Ecuadorian authorities of the locations of the bodies and how the sadistic crimes were committed, he showed no feelings of remorse. After raping his victims, he had hacked, slashed and crushed the girls with a [[machete]]. He gave a cynical explanation for choosing children. He wanted virgins "because they cried"; this apparently gave him greater satisfaction. According to Camargo, he killed because he wanted revenge on woman's unfaithfulness. He hated them for not being what he believed women were supposed to be.

==Interview==
In June 1986 Francisco Febres Cordero, a journalist for the newspaper ''[[Hoy (Ecuadorian newspaper)|Hoy]]'' (Today), managed to arrange an interview with Camargo. It was difficult to get the interview due to the police blocking all access to Camargo, and the fact that Camargo himself demanded a large fee before he would let himself be interviewed. The journalist pretended to be part of a group of psychologists that were allowed access to the prisoner, allowing him to ask Camargo questions without arousing his suspicion.&lt;ref name="Infants and Virginity" /&gt;

==Sentence==
Camargo was convicted in 1989 and sentenced to 16 years in prison, the maximum sentence available in Ecuador. While serving his sentence in the Garcia Moreno de Quito jail, he claimed to have converted to [[Christianity]]. In this penitentiary he was imprisoned with
[[Pedro López (serial killer)|Pedro Alonso López]] (also dubbed "the Monster of the Andes"), who is believed to have raped and killed more than 300 girls in Colombia, Ecuador and [[Peru]].

==Death==
On 13 November 1994, Camargo was stabbed to death in prison by Geovanny Noguera, who turned out to be the nephew of one of the victims. He was 64 years old at the time of his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.eltiempo.com/archivo/documento/MAM-250868# |title=Archived copy |access-date=1 June 2015 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150610174559/http://www.eltiempo.com/archivo/documento/MAM-250868# |archive-date=10 June 2015 |url-status=live |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://murderpedia.org/male.C/c/camargo-barbosa.htm Entry at murderpedia.org]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Barbosa, Daniel Camargo}}
[[Category:1936 births]]
[[Category:1994 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century criminals]]
[[Category:Colombian escapees]]
[[Category:Colombian murderers of children]]
[[Category:Colombian people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:Colombian people imprisoned abroad]]
[[Category:Colombian people murdered abroad]]
[[Category:Colombian people who died in prison custody]]
[[Category:Colombian rapists]]
[[Category:Colombian serial killers]]
[[Category:People from Cundinamarca Department]]
[[Category:Violence against women in Colombia]]
[[Category:Escapees from Colombian detention]]
[[Category:Male serial killers]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Ecuador]]
[[Category:Prisoners who died in Ecuadorian detention]]
[[Category:Serial killers murdered in prison custody]]
[[Category:People deported from Brazil]]
[[Category:1986 crimes in Ecuador]]
[[Category:1986 murders in South America]]
[[Category:1980s murders in Ecuador]]</text>
      <sha1>lhz8t57wfuiiltd7mozt6tiprjydui8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
