<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.35.0-wmf.22</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Marc Dutroux</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>154694</id>
    <revision>
      <id>944210888</id>
      <parentid>944209796</parentid>
      <timestamp>2020-03-06T12:00:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lebob</username>
        <id>2808799</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 944209796 by [[Special:Contributions/Woman on a mission|Woman on a mission]] ([[User talk:Woman on a mission|talk]]) This list is inaccurate and is based on poor or unacceptable sources, on sources that do not match with the content of the article or even on no sources at all. Please go through the talk page before trying to restore again this garbage.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="97867" xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues|
{{Disputed|date=December 2019}}
{{Condense|date=December 2019}}

}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2018}}
{{Infobox criminal
| name = Marc Dutroux
| image = 
| caption = 
| alt = 
| birthname = Marc Paul Alain Dutroux
| alias = 
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1956|11|06|df=yes}}
| birth_place = [[Ixelles]], Belgium
| spouse = Francoise D. &lt;br /&gt;(1976&amp;ndash;1983)&lt;br /&gt; Michelle Martin&lt;br /&gt; (1989&amp;ndash;2003)
| children = 5
| country = Belgium
| date = 19??–1986, 1995–1996
| partners = Michelle Martin, &lt;br /&gt;Michel Lelièvre
| victims = 11 (possibly more)
| fatalities = 5
| apprehended = 13 August 1996
| penalty = [[Life imprisonment in Belgium|Life imprisonment]]
| conviction = {{Unbulleted list|Child pornography|Child sexual abuse|Kidnapping|Murder|Theft}}
| conviction_status = Imprisoned&lt;br /&gt;(solitary confinement)
| imprisoned = Prison of [[Nivelles]]
}}

[[File:En-us-Marc Dutroux from Belgium pronunciation (Voice of America).ogg|thumb|Marc Dutroux from Belgium pronunciation ([[Voice of America]])]]
'''Marc Paul Alain Dutroux'''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nieuwsblad.be/cnt/hno19022004_071|title=Het mirakel van Marcinelle|date=31 January 2004|work=[[Het Nieuwsblad]]|access-date=14 June 2018|language=nl-BE|trans-title=The miracle of Marcinelle}}&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPA-fr|dytʀu|lang}}; born 6 November 1956) is a Belgian convicted child molester and murderer.

Dutroux was convicted in 1989 for the abduction and rape of five young girls (with his then-wife Michelle Martin) and other accomplices. He was released on parole after three years in prison.

In 1996, Dutroux was arrested on suspicion of having kidnapped, tortured and sexually abused six females aged between 8 and 19, four of whom died. His widely publicised trial took place in 2004. Dutroux was convicted of all charges, along with the murder of a suspected former accomplice, and sentenced to life imprisonment. Martin was convicted as an accomplice to 30 years in prison. Another accomplice Michel Lièvre was convicted to 25 years in prison. Michel Nihoul was first trialed with Marc Dutroux but then convicted in a separate case to five years in prison. Another accomplice of Marc Dutroux, Bernard Weinstein, was killed by him and thus never trialed.

A number of shortcomings in the Dutroux investigation caused widespread discontent in Belgium with the country's criminal justice system, and the ensuing scandal was one of the reasons for the reorganisation of [[Law enforcement in Belgium|Belgium's law enforcement]] agencies and widespread allegations of corruption and infiltration of the Belgian justice system by a criminal enterprise. In the [[White March]], 300,000 Belgian citizens protested the mishandling of the case.

==Early life and early criminal career==
Born in [[Ixelles]], Belgium, on 6 November 1956,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|year=2009|title=Marc Dutroux|encyclopedia=[[Encyclopædia Britannica]]|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1012618/Marc-Dutroux|date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dutroux was the eldest child of five of Victor and Jeanine, who were both teachers. He spent the first years of his life in Congo. After the Congo crisis his parents had to return to Belgium.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"&gt;{{cite web|year=2009|title=Marc Dutroux|publisher=murderpedia|url=https://murderpedia.org/male.D/d/dutroux-marc.htm|date=}} {{unreliable?|date=November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dutroux reported that he was repeatedly beaten by his parents. His parents divorced in 1971 and Dutroux left home. He then became a drifter and a male prostitute.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt; Dutroux married at age 20 and had two children. He admitted to beating his wife and cheating on her. They separated in the 1980s.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt; One of his mistresses was Michelle Martin, who he later married and had three more children with.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt; Dutroux and Martin were married in 1989 while both were in prison. They divorced in 2003, also while in prison.{{citation needed|date=May 2019}}

===Early release of Dutroux after abduction and rapes===
Dutroux had already committed similar crimes (kidnapping and rape of young girls). He had been imprisoned for that in 1989.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Trueheart |first1=Charles |title=SORDID TIMES IN DEAR BELGIUM' |url=http://archive.is/jxiLV#selection-3715.53-3715.70|website=washingtonpost.com |publisher=The Washington Post |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was however released early and was thus able to reoffend. Namely he was released in 1991 after only serving three and a half years of a thirteen-year sentence.&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt;&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Vos |first1=Elizabeth Lea |title=The Revelations of WikiLeaks: No. 4—The Haunting Case of a Belgian Child Killer and How WikiLeaks Helped Crack It |url=https://consortiumnews.com/2019/07/11/the-revelations-of-wikileaks-no-4-the-haunting-case-of-a-belgian-child-killer-and-how-wikileaks-helped-crack-it/ |website=consortiumnews.com |publisher=consortiumnews |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dutroux abducted Axelle D. on 14 December 1985. During her testimony, she told the police that Dutroux's accomplice Peteghem had told her that "he was part of a gang" led by two gang leaders, "an Italian and a crazy stupid one." Jean van Peteghem admitted to have taken part in the abduction. He said he had abducted Axelle D. with Marc Dutroux and Michelle Martin. He had lived with Dutroux after being discharged from the military and having his marriage fail. Peteghem told police that the first victims of his and Dutroux were two girls from Morlanwelz. These two victims were never recovered by police. On 7 June 1985 the first proven abduction by the two took place. They abducted eleven-year-old Sylvie D.. On 17 October 1985 the pair abducted Maria V., 19, from Peronnes-lez-Binche. Maria V. also identified a third man that took part in her abduction and appeared to be in his fifties. The man was never found by police. On 17 January 1986 Catherine B., 18, was abducted from Obaix. Dutroux had one or two accomplices in her abduction that were never found by police. Peteghem was stationed as army personnel in Germany during that time and could not have assisted Dutroux. On 18 December 1985, Dutroux abducted Elisabeth G., 15, in Pont-à-Celles. Peteghem told police that Dutroux filmed Elisabeth naked and took pictures of her. At the beginning of February 1987, Martin, Dutroux and Peteghem were arrested. This had to a large extent been the fault of Peteghem who had given out a lot of information about him in conversations with the girls, which had been enough for police to identify him. The three were eventually convicted on 26 April 1989. Dutroux received 13.5 years. Peteghem received 6.5 years and Martin received 5 years. Dutroux received a harsher sentence because he had also committed several robberies with Peteghem. Dutroux was thus additionally convicted for the brutal robbery of a 58-year-old woman. The robbery was also committed with accomplices. One of the accomplices in this robbery was also never found by police.&lt;ref name="nieuwsbald"&gt;{{cite web |title=Dutroux had zijn lesje geleerd |url=https://www.nieuwsblad.be/cnt/hno19022004_049 |website=nieuwsblad.be |publisher=Bieuwsblad |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The early release of Dutroux was against the advice of the public prosecutor and against the advice of the psychiatrist who had examined him in prison and stated that he remained dangerous.&lt;ref name="nieuwsbald"/&gt;

The early release was granted by [[Melchior Wathelet]].&lt;ref name="zeit"&gt;{{cite web |title=Die Spuren führen zu den Einflußreichen |url=https://www.zeit.de/2004/10/dutroux2 |website=zeit.de |publisher=Die Zeit |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Melchior Wathelet was at that time the Belgian minister of justice.

===Granting Dutroux state assistance, sleeping pills and sedatives===
While in jail Dutroux managed to convince a health professional that he was disabled because of mental illness. He thus was able to collect public assistance by the Belgium government of $1,200 a month. He, furthermore, convinced the professional that he needed sedatives for sleeping problems. Dutroux later went on to use those sedatives to sedate his victims.&lt;ref&gt;ok|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7umgCOBEMgEC&amp;pg=PA86&amp;lpg=PA86&amp;sig=0dGQs7ptXQcOK6NWGkN91cUT7rU&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwA2oVChMIwOKpq8GlxwIVyjkaCh0OnQYf#v=onepage&amp;q=Charleroi%20high%20unemployment%201990s|title=Globalization and Integrated Area Development in European Cities|last=Moulaert|first=Frank|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=2000|isbn=|location=|page=86|pages=}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= https://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/financialcrisis/5072276/Charleroi-the-most-depressing-city-in-Europe-becomes-more-depressing-by-the-day.html| date= 29 March 2009| title= Charleroi: the most depressing city in Europe becomes more depressing by the day |newspaper= The Telegraph| accessdate= 20 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He owned seven small houses, most of them vacant, and used three of them for the torture of the girls he kidnapped. Even though he owned several houses his state assistance wasn't cut. In his residence in [[Marcinelle]], he constructed a concealed dungeon in the basement. Dutroux has been described by [[psychiatrist]]s who examined him for trial as a [[Psychopathy|psychopath]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraphindia.com/1040618/asp/foreign/story_3385982.asp|title=Evil Belgian found guilty|last=|first=|date=17 June 2002|work=[[The Telegraph India]]|location=Calcutta|accessdate=13 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Crimes after release==
On 24 June 1995, eight-year-old classmates Julie Lejeune and Mélissa Russo were kidnapped after going for a walk in [[Grâce-Hollogne]], probably by Dutroux,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/01/world/europe/accomplice-in-belgian-child-killings-paroled-to-convent.html|title=Accomplice in Belgian child killings paroled to convent|last=|first=|date=31 July 2012|work=|access-date=12 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and brought to his house in Marcinelle. Dutroux kept them imprisoned in the dungeon he had created, repeatedly sexually abused them and produced [[Child pornography|pornographic]] videos of the abuse. Two months later, in the early hours of 23 August in [[Ostend]], Dutroux and accomplice Michel Lelièvre kidnapped An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks, two teenage girls from [[Hasselt]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.trouw.nl/home/steeds-vond-vader-marchal-een-woord~a1a22a15/|title=Steeds vond vader Marchal een woord|last=|first=|date=|website=[[Trouw]]|language=nl-NL|access-date=26 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; who were on their way back to their holiday home in [[Westende]] following a night out in [[Blankenberge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lalibre.be/archive/an-et-eefje-jusqu-au-bout-de-l-horreur-51b88269e4b0de6db9a9d83b|title=An et Eefje, jusqu'au bout de l'horreur|date=|work=[[La Libre Belgique]]|access-date=24 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; With Lejeune and Russo already in the dungeon, Lambrecks and Marchal were kept chained up in a bedroom. In September, according to Martin, Lambrecks and Marchal were drugged and brought to [[Jumet]], where Dutroux and accomplice Bernard Weinstein killed them by burying them in a hole.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lalibre.be/actu/belgique/an-et-eefje-enterrees-vivantes-sans-doute-en-septembre-95-51b882e5e4b0de6db9a9febf|title=An et Eefje enterrées vivantes, sans doute en septembre 95|date=|work=La Libre Belgique|access-date=26 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Around the time of Lambrecks and Marchal's deaths, Weinstein and a man named Philippe Divers stole a van and hid it in a hangar; after it was found there by the hangar's owner, it was taken away by the police. Dutroux and Weinstein suspected that Divers and his friend Pierre Rochow had betrayed them, and on the night of 4 November, wishing to interrogate them about the van, Dutroux and Weinstein lured Divers and Rochow into Weinstein's home in Jumet and drugged and sequestered them, before leaving to go to Rochow's house to search for clues about the van. There they found his girlfriend Bénédicte Jadot, whom they took with them back to Jumet and questioned before leaving again to pick up another person. While they were away, Jadot escaped and alerted a neighbour, who called the police.&lt;ref name="Je ne voulais pas les supprimer"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lalibre.be/actu/belgique/je-ne-voulais-pas-les-supprimer-51b88369e4b0de6db9aa1f8d|title="Je ne voulais pas les supprimer"|date=|work=La Libre Belgique|access-date=26 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.dhnet.be/actu/faits/dutroux-m-aurait-tuee-51b7ca7de4b0de6db98e5a1f|title=''Dutroux m'aurait tuée''|date=|work=[[La Dernière Heure]]|access-date=26 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; With Weinstein wanted by police, Dutroux decided to kill him to prevent his capture. He kidnapped Weinstein and held him in the dungeon at his house in Marcinelle between 13 and 20 November. During this time, he let Lejeune and Russo roam freely around the house. After feeding him food laced with [[Flunitrazepam|Rohypnol]], Dutroux placed [[hose clamp]]s around Weinstein's testicles until Weinstein told him where his money was hidden. Dutroux then killed Weinstein by burying him in a hole on his (Dutroux's) property in [[Sars-la-Buissière]].&lt;ref name="La Dernière Heure"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.dhnet.be/archive/bernard-weinstein-torture-avec-des-colliers-de-serrage-51b82fa2e4b0de6db9a061bc|title=Bernard Weinstein torturé avec des colliers de serrage|date=|work=La Dernière Heure|access-date=26 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December, Dutroux, having been recognised by Rochow, was arrested.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

According to Dutroux and Martin, Lejeune and Russo were still alive in the house at the time of Dutroux's arrest in December, and Dutroux had ordered Martin to leave new food and water for the girls in the dungeon each time they ran out. Martin neglected to feed them, later claiming she was too afraid to go into the dungeon.&lt;ref name="Van Heeswyck 1999"&gt;Van Heeswyck, Marie-Jeanne; Bulté, Annemie; De Coninck, Douglas; ''The X-Dossiers'', 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Lejeune and Russo eventually starved to death. Dutroux initially stated that they were still alive when he returned home following his release from prison on 20 March 1996; according to him, Lejeune died that day, and Russo followed suit four days later despite his efforts to save her; during his trial, he said they were already dead when he returned from prison.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lalibre.be/actu/belgique/langloisjulie-et-melissa-sont-mortes-de-faim-et-de-soif-51b882e5e4b0de6db9a9fe82|title=Langlois: "Julie et Mélissa sont mortes de faim et de soif"|date=|work=La Libre Belgique|access-date=27 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=":2"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lesoir.be/archive/recup/le-calvaire-de-julie-et-melissa-martin-et-le-mystere-de_t-20040310-Z0P4PC.html|title=Le calvaire de Julie et Melissa Martin et le mystère de la lourde porte|date=|work=[[Le Soir]]|access-date=28 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; An expert asserted that they would not have been able to survive the entire time Dutroux was in prison on the total amount of food and water they were said to have been given.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.standaard.be/cnt/nflb18032004_001|title=Julie en Melissa konden geen 103 dagen overleven|date=|work=[[De Standaard]]|access-date=27 June 2018|language=nl-BE}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dutroux buried Lejeune and Russo's bodies in the garden of the house he owned in Sars-la-Buissière, near to that of Weinstein.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.nouvelobs.com/societe/20110510.OBS2805/dutroux-meurtrier-violeur-et-dealer-d-enfants.html|title=Dutroux, meurtrier, violeur et dealer d'enfants|last=|first=|date=|work=[[L'Obs]]|access-date=27 June 2018|language=fr-FR}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the morning of 28 May 1996, Dutroux and Lelièvre kidnapped 12-year-old [[Sabine Dardenne]], who was cycling to school in [[Tournai]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.dhnet.be/actu/faits/le-pedophile-dutroux-raconte-par-sabine-51b7d031e4b0de6db98fae63|title=Le pédophile Dutroux raconté par Sabine!|last=|first=|date=|work=La Dernière Heure|access-date=28 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a book originally published under the title ''J'avais 12 ans, j'ai pris mon vélo et je suis partie à l'école''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lesoir.be/archive/d-20050121-W2EC0U |title=Dutroux - Le livre s'arrache Sabine cartonne |language=fr |first=Marc |last=Metdepenningen |work=Le Soir |date=21 January 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (and published in the United Kingdom under the title ''I Choose to Live''), Dardenne described her time in captivity in Dutroux's Marcinelle home, where she spent most of the time imprisoned in the dungeon and was starved and repeatedly raped by Dutroux.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2005/may/15/biography.features1|title=Observer review: I Choose to Live by Sabine Dardenne|last=France|first=Louise|date=15 May 2005|website=the Guardian|language=en|access-date=28 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 August, Dutroux and Lelièvre kidnapped 14-year-old Laetitia Delhez as she was walking home from her local swimming pool in [[Bertrix]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.lalibre.be/actu/belgique/dutroux-et-lelievre-ont-prepare-l-enlevement-de-laetitia-51b882e5e4b0de6db9a9fee8|title=Dutroux et Lelièvre ont préparé l'enlèvement de Laetitia|last=Libre.be|first=La|access-date=28 June 2018|language=fr}}&lt;/ref&gt; An eyewitness observed Dutroux's van, described it and was able to identify part of the [[license plate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.rtbf.be/info/dossier/l-affaire-dutroux-20-ans-plus-tard/detail_les-25-personnages-clefs-de-l-affaire-dutroux-les-2-temoins-de-bertrix?id=9370372|title=Les 25 personnages clefs de l'affaire Dutroux: les 2 témoins de Bertrix|date=9 August 2016|work=RTBF Info|access-date=28 June 2018|language=fr-FR}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 August, Dutroux, Martin and Lelièvre were arrested.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3794985.stm |title=Timeline: Dutroux paedophile case |date=17 June 2004 |work=BBC News |access-date=11 August 2018 |language=en-GB }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/belgians-furious-as-child-killer-marc-dutrouxs-wife-michelle-martin-is-freed-8091716.html |title= Belgian furious as child killer Marc Dutroux wife Michelle is freed| agency= Associated Press| date= 22 August 2012| website= The Independent| accessdate= 12 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; An initial search of Dutroux's houses proved inconclusive, but two days later, Dutroux and Lelièvre both made confessions. That same day, Dutroux led the police to the basement dungeon inside which Dardenne and Delhez were imprisoned, and the girls were subsequently rescued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |people= |year=2008 |title=Serial Killers: Monster of Belgium |url= |format= |medium=Television Production |language= |trans_title= |publisher=Discovery Communications |location=Silver Spring, Maryland, US |accessdate= |time= |id= |isbn= |oclc= |quote= |ref= }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 August, Dutroux led police to his house in Sars-la-Buissière, and with his help they were able to locate and exhume the bodies of Lejeune, Russo and Weinstein.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.lesoir.be/archive/recup/%252Fhorreur-pour-julie-et-melissa-fragile-espoir-pour-an-et_t-19960819-Z0CH97.html |title=Horreur Pour Julie et Melissa,Fragile Espoir Pour An et Eefje Chronique d'Epouvante la Bonne Piste une Vie de Flic |last=Guillaume |first=Alain |date=19 August 1996 |work=Le Soir |access-date=10 August 2018 |language=fr }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 September, the remains of Marchal and Lambrecks were located and exhumed in Jumet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lesoir.be/archive/d-19960904-W346XJ |title=Dutroux - Le livre s'arrache Sabine cartonne |language=fr |work=Le Soir}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hundreds of commercial adult pornographic videos, along with a large number of home-made sex films that Dutroux had made with Martin, were recovered from his properties.&lt;ref name=murder&gt;{{cite web|last=Bell|first=Rachael|title=Marc Dutroux, A Pedophile and Child-Killer|url=http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/predators/dutroux/evil_1.html|publisher=trutv|accessdate=19 December 2012|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121210082737/http://www.trutv.com/library/crime/serial_killers/predators/dutroux/evil_1.html|archive-date=10 December 2012|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Grave errors by law enforcement and prosecution during investigation==
===Failure to follow up on letter of Dutroux's mother warning of kidnapped girls being held at his house===
In 1995 Dutroux's mother wrote a letter to the authorities stating that she knew that Dutroux had kidnapped two girls and was keeping them at his house.&lt;ref name="britannica"/&gt;

===Failure to rescue Melissa and Julie===
After Melissa and Julie were kidnapped in 1995, it took police 14 months to arrest Dutroux even though he had been a prime suspect from the start and had committed similar crimes before.&lt;ref name="guardian"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Frenkiel |first1=Olenka |title=Belgium's silent heart of darkness |url=http://archive.is/rUKk6 |website=guardian.co.uk |publisher=the guardian |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
During the search for Melissa and Julie, police visited Dutroux's house twice on 13 December and 19 December where Julie and Melissa were held. However, no attempts were made to free them, even though the locksmith who accompanied the police, René Michaux,&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; said that he heard screams of children coming from inside the house. The locksmith repeatedly said: "I'm not leaving before we turn the place upside down. The screams are clearly coming from inside the house." To which Michaux replied: "Who is the police officer here? You or me?"&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt;

===Dutroux arrest on car theft charges===
Around the time of Eefje Lambrecks and An Marchal's deaths, Weinstein and a man named Philippe Divers stole a van and hid it in a hangar; after it was found there by the hangar's owner, it was taken away by the police. Dutroux and Weinstein suspected that Divers and his friend Pierre Rochow had betrayed them, and on the night of 4 November, wishing to interrogate them about the van, Dutroux and Weinstein lured Divers and Rochow into Weinstein's home in Jumet and drugged and sequestered them, before leaving to go to Rochow's house to search for clues about the van. There they found his girlfriend Bénédicte Jadot, whom they took with them back to Jumet and questioned before leaving again to pick up another person. While they were away, Jadot escaped and alerted a neighbour, who called the police.&lt;ref name="Je ne voulais pas les supprimer"/&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"/&gt; With Weinstein wanted by police, Dutroux decided to kill him to prevent capture. He kidnapped Weinstein and held him in the dungeon at his house in Marcinelle between 13 and 20 November. During this time, he let Julie Lejeune and Melissa Russo roam freely around the house. After feeding him food laced with [[Flunitrazepam|Rohypnol]], Dutroux placed [[hose clamp]]s around Weinstein's testicles until Weinstein told him where his money was hidden. Dutroux then killed Weinstein by burying him in a hole on his (Dutroux's) property in [[Sars-la-Buissière]].&lt;ref name="La Dernière Heure"/&gt; In December, Dutroux, having been recognised by Rochow, was arrested.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

Marc Dutroux was arrested on 6 December 1995 on car theft charges and subsequently convicted to three months in jail.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt; During the three months Melissa and Julie died of starvation and dehydration in their dungeon cell as the wife of Dutroux didn't feed them, even though she knew that they were there.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

===Failure to review video tapes confiscated from Dutroux===
During the search of the houses of Marc Dutroux several video tapes were found. Those were never looked at. Some of them showed Dutroux constructing the dungeon in which Melissa and Julie were held. Had police looked at it, they would have found the dungeon and Melissa and Julie.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; The video tapes had been in possession of the police since December 1995. They had been passed on the to the prosecutors in the case but not to the judges.&lt;ref name="guardianvideo"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Bates |first1=Stephan |title=Police admit Dutroux video bungle |url=http://archive.is/UjFPC |website=guardian.co.uk |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, some of the video tapes were actually returned to Dutroux by police officer René Michauxm without ever being looked at.

The later leading investigator Michel Bourlet said that some of the video tapes had disappeared and that he want to have them all recovered and reviewed.&lt;ref name="dhnet"/&gt;

The videos were reportedly stolen after they were returned to Dutroux.&lt;ref name="dhnet"/&gt; In 1999 some of the tapes were finally reviewed. One of them showed Dutroux raping a young woman in Slovakia.&lt;ref name="dhnet"/&gt; The videos could have made it possible to identify other victims and also exactly determine the severity of the torture that the victims had to endure during their ordeal.&lt;ref name="dhnet"/&gt;

Later during the trial the lawyer of one of the victims, Laetitia Delhez, also expressed disappointment that the videos weren't reviewed, because they could have proved that Dutroux wasn't acting alone.&lt;ref name="dhnet"/&gt;

===Escape of Dutroux in 1998===
In 1998 Dutroux was allowed to have a look at his case files. He was accompanied by two police officers for that. When one officer went on a break Dutroux overwhelmed the other officer and was able to escape. He was captured a few hours later.&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt; The Minister of Justice [[Stefaan De Clerck]], the Minister of the Interior [[Johan Vande Lanotte]], and the police chief resigned as a result. In 2000, Dutroux received a five-year sentence for threatening a police officer during his escape. In 2002, he received another five-year sentence for unrelated crimes.&lt;ref name=murder /&gt;&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt;

===Failure to analyse DNA from basement dungeon===
Thousands of hairs were found in the cellar dungeon where Melissa and Julie were held. However those were for a very long time not tested for DNA.&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt;

===Inquiry into officer De Baets handling of the police investigation===
An inquiry was initiated into the way the investigation was handled by officer De Baets. As this inquiry into his handling of the case took up a lot of resources and during the inquiry it wasn't possible for him to pass on information to the Parliamentary inquiry into the handling of the case, crucial time was lost.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt;

There were accusations that language difficulties obscured the investigation. The testimony of Régina Louf was in Dutch, however it was reviewed several times by the new investigators who were primarily French speaking and they had difficulties in understanding her. Thus they changed the meaning of her testimony in a way that made her sound less credible.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt;

===Failure to properly investigate leads to Slovakia and Czech Republic===
Several sources said that Michel Nihoul and Marc Dutroux were planning on a prostitution and trafficking operation between Slovakia, the Czech Republic and western Europe. Several pieces of evidence lead to connections to Slovakia and the Czech Republic. This included a video tape of Dutroux raping a young woman in Slovakia that wasn't reviewed after it was seized. It also included testimonies saying that they were planning on setting up a trafficking operation. Also the car theft and smuggling operation that Dutroux was involved in lead to those two Eastern European countries. During the time of his arrest Dutroux was in the possession of 2.000 SKK (Slovakian currency) in cash. Six Belgian investigators visited the Czech Republic and Slovakia in August 1996. It wasn't possible to proof that Dutroux had committed any crimes while being there. Thus they returned without any substantial evidence.&lt;ref name="kriminalistika"&gt;{{cite web |title=Marc Dutroux |url=http://kriminalistika.eu/muzeumzla/dutroux/dutroux.html |website=kriminalistika.eu |publisher=kriminalistika |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accusations of cover-up==
Many Belgian people believed that Dutroux was part of a paedophile network, that included high- ranking members of the Belgian establishment and that the other people involved were never prosecuted.&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Helm |first1=Toby |title=Belgium accused of cover-up in Dutroux inquiry |url=http://archive.is/LxSWS#selection-607.14-607.26 |website=telegraph.co.uk |publisher=telegraph |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judge Jean-Marc Connerottes removal from the case===
Press reports claimed that before his removal judge Jean-Marc Connerotte was on the verge of publicly disclosing the names of high level government officials who had been recognized on video-tapes.&lt;ref name="nyt"/&gt; Judge Jean-Marc Connerotte had said that the business man Michel Nihoul was the brains behind the child kidnapping operation.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Investigators also believed that Dutroux and Nihoul were planning on a long-distance prostitution trafficking network involving cars and the import of girls from Slovakia.&lt;ref name="bbc"/&gt;

The investigating police said in 1996, that Dutroux was part of a child-prostitution ring, that may also have been responsible for several other disappearances still unsolved. They also said that the gang surround Dutroux offered $5.000 per girl they received. Their criminal activities also involved car theft.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost"/&gt; It was said that the criminal network around Dutroux was involved in car theft and smuggling. The car in which Melissa and Julie were kidnapped has never been found. The general prosecutor, Anne Thilly, decided to have the car theft and smuggling be investigated by different police authorities in different parts of the country. In this way it was nearly impossible to investigate the connection between the car theft, kidnapping and human trafficking.&lt;ref name="bbc"/&gt; Dutroux also said that Nihoul had proposed to traffic girls from Eastern countries.&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt;

Michel Lelièvre the accomplice of Marc Dutroux said that the two girls Melissa and Julie were kidnapped as an order by a third party. However while in arrest Lelièvre stopped cooperating with the authorities.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; He told police that he had been threatened and couldn't risk saying any more.&lt;ref name="bbc"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Frenkiel |first1=Olenka |title=Dutroux and the network|url= https://archive.is/amK88|website=washingtonpost.com |publisher=BBC |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The father of Melissa Russo, Gino Russo, said during the White March that the removal of judge Connerotte was like "''spitting on the grave of Julie and Melissa''." Russo subsequently said that after Connerotte was removed there was no progress in the investigation.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

===Dutrouxs wealth and assets===
Dutroux owned ten houses. He was in total worth 6 million [[Belgian franc|Belgian Francs]] (130,000 [[United States dollar|USD]]).&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt; While he had all of this wealth in property he also received public assistance of $1.200 a month. It isn't clear how Dutroux was able to acquire the ten properties. Documents were released by Wikileaks that show that large sums of money in different currencies arrived in Michelle Martins bank account timely linked to the disappearances of the abducted girls.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost"/&gt; The money was also transferred in foreign currencies from Morocco and Saudi Arabia.&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt; Both the transfers and the value of the six properties that Dutroux owned suggested to investigators that he was financed by a larger pedophile and prostitution ring.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt; The Flemish newspaper Nieuwsblad reported that he had committed health insurance fund fraud, theft, insurance fraud and investments on the stock market and that that had contributed to his wealth.&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"&gt;{{cite web |title=Dutroux had zijn lesje geleerd |url=https://www.nieuwsblad.be/cnt/hno19022004_049 |website=nieuwsblad.be |publisher=Nieuwsblad |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other outlets suggested that he was able to acquire his wealth through criminal activity such as drug-trafficking and insurance fraud.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt; Additional sources said that he made a lot of money with car theft and pimping.&lt;ref name="britannica"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Jenkins |first1=John Philip |title=Marc Dutroux |url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Marc-Dutroux |website=britannica.com |publisher=Encyclopedia Britannica |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Claims by the victims families===
The father of one of the murdered girls, Paul Marchal, the father of An Marchal accused the police and the judicial system of a cover-up in 2001. He was angry that still in 2001 the trial hadn't started even though Dutroux had already been under arrest for several years. Paul Marchal said: "''It feels like they don't want to find the truth. It is not a good feeling and not only I think this''."&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt;

Carine Russo and her husband Gino Russo were not permitted to identify her daughter and look at her body. They were told by authorities that Dutroux had identified her and that that was enough.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; The autopsy of Melissa showed that she had been raped repeatedly over a prolonged period of time. No DNA evidence was taken from the body to conclusively make sure that only Dutroux had raped her. Dutroux always denied raping Melissa and Julie.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

Eventually several families of victims boycotted the official trial stating that it was a circus and there had been no progress in the case since the removal of judge Connerottes.&lt;ref name="telegraphmurder"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Evans-Pritchard |first1=Ambrose |title=Judge tells of murder plots to block Dutroux investigation |url=http://archive.is/imzXd |website=telegraph.co.uk |publisher=telegraph |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Failure to test hairs in the dungeon for DNA evidence===
There were countless hairs found in the dungeon where the two girls were held. The judge Langlois refused to have them tested for DNA evidence even though the leading police investigator Michel Bourlet had begged him to have them analyzed in order to know whether more people aside from Dutroux were involved.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; The general prosecutor of the case, Anne Thily, said that she didn't believe that there was anyone else involved and thus didn't have the samples analyzed.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Thily told investigative journalist Frenkiel that: "''In any case the hairs have all now been analysed - all 5,000.' And the results of this analysis? Nothing. No evidence of any relevance in the Dutroux affair. Which proves, of course, that Langlois was right all along''." But according to Frenkiel this wasn't true. Sources central to the investigation confirmed that in 2002 the hairs had still not been analysed. Thus Frenkiel accused the senior prosecutor Thily of lying brasantly.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Frenkiel continued to question Thily and asked her how she would want to prove that Dutroux raped the girls, as he was denying it and there was no DNA evidence. Thily then replied that there were DNA tests, but that the results came back inconclusive as the bodies were too decomposed at the time the samples were taken.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Dutroux's lawyer, Xavier Magnee, said during the trial proceedings "I speak not only as a lawyer, but also as a citizen and father. He was not the only devil. Out of the 6.000 hair samples that were found in the basement cellar where some of the victims were held, 25 "unknown" DNA profiles were discovered. There were people in that cellar that are not now accused." However it was never attempted by the prosecution to match those DNA profiles to people implicated in the case. .&lt;ref name="independentpolicehelp"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Castle|first1=Stephen|title=Dutroux says he abducted girls with police help|url=http://archive.is/jUDPQ#selection-3877.0-3877.47|website=independent |publisher=Independent |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Magnee also said that the prosecutors didn’t follow up on evidence leading to a cult called "Abrasax", which allegedly performed human sacrifices.&lt;ref name="independentpolicehelp"/&gt; In a wooden house of Bernard Weinstein (accomplice of Dutroux) a letter was found from the occult sect "Abrasax", in which a gift for the high priestress (Dominique Kindermans)&lt;ref name="irishtimes"&gt;{{cite web |last1=LOVELL |first1=JEREMY |title=Police raid centre of satanic sect |url=https://www.irishtimes.com/news/police-raid-centre-of-satanic-sect-1.118865 |website=irishtimes.com |publisher=irish times |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; was mentioned consisting of 17 girls between the age of 2 and 20 for anal, oral and vaginal sex. It was signed by priest "Anubis". This priest was later identified as Francis Desmedt. Later investigations showed that four police men in Charleroi were also members of the sect, one was even the treasurer.&lt;ref name="spiegel"&gt;{{cite web |title=KINDESMISSBRAUCH "Kleine blonde Pferdchen" |url=https://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-8680123.html |website=spiegel.de |publisher=spiegel |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; The headquarter of the sect (Institut Abrasax) in Rue Emile Vandervelde 223 Forchies La Marche was raided in 1996 by 150 officers. The television showed police taking away bags of papers, video cassettes and a refrigerator. They also took away black magic ritual implements and human skulls.&lt;ref name="irishtimes"/&gt;

===Removal of police officers from the case===
Several police officer that had worked on the case were subsequently removed in 1997. They were reportedly removed because they had manipulated evidence surrounding the testimony of Régina Louf. However the involved officers always denied that accusation. This included officer Rudi Hoskens, who believed that the testimony of witness X1, Régina Louf, was true because her testimony matched an unsolved murder case that she could have had no knowledge on, had she not witnessed it. What she described was the murder of then 15 year old Christine van Hees. She said that the girl was tortured to death by the group and that Nihoul took part in the torture. She said Dutroux watched. Christine's body was found in 1984.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; The officer leading the investigation, Mr. De Baets, said that they followed up on all testimonies the X witnesses had given, in order to determine whether what they said was possible or not and that they came to the conclusion that it was possible that the things had occurred as the witnesses described them. As this took up a lot of resources and time of the police force an inquiry was initiated into the handling of the case, which then again took up as much resources as the investigation of Mr. De Baets itself. It was said that: "''The suspicion grew that De Baets and others formed part of a sect bent on destabilising the kingdom''." So De Baets and large parts of his team were removed from the investigation and sent home on indefinite leave.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt; Not only was De Baets dropped from the investigation, he was also charged in 1997 with concealing the fact that Louf had wrongly identified the photograph of one of the victims. However, on the video tapes of her interrogation it is visible that it was very hard for her to stand looking at the photographs and that her right answer had been in the files all along. In 1999 De Baets was exhonerated from the charges.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt; Additionally two journalists from Le Soir Illustre, who had defamed him and four colleagues were convicted to pay two of them 55.000 $ plus court costs.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt; Even though De Baets had been exhonerated, he and his colleagues remained on leave.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt;

===Promotion of René Michaux, who failed to save Julie and Melissa===
The officer that searched Dutrouxs house while Julie and Melissa were likely still alive on 13 and 19 December 1995. However even though the locksmith that he inspected the house with suggested they should search the whole house to find out where children's screams were coming from, Michaux left after not having searched the house thoroughly.&lt;ref name="dhnet"&gt;{{cite web |title=Procès Dutroux: Michaux à la barre |url=http://archive.is/MTgi4 |website=dhnet.be |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Not only did Michaux fail to rescue Julie and Melissa, he also failed to look at video tapes that were confiscated from Dutroux's house. Those video tapes showed him constructing the dungeon, which would have led them to the place where Julie and Melissa were kept. Some of the videos also included tapes of Dutroux raping women. Many of the tapes were returned to Dutroux without ever being looked at by law enforcement.&lt;ref name="dhnet"/&gt;

Even though René Michaux committed grave failures in his duty as a police officer in what was one of the most important criminal cases in the history of Belgium, he was never removed or put on leave like other officers had been. He was subsequently promoted to the position of police commissioner.&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt;

===Arrests of law enforcement personal believed to be connected to Dutroux===
At least seven members of law enforcement were arrested on suspicion of having ties to Marc Dutroux. One of them was Georges Zico a police detective believed to be an associate of Dutroux.&lt;ref name="independent"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Brace |first1=Matthew |title=Detective held in Belgian abuse case |url=http://archive.is/fUnKU#selection-4279.0-4279.12 |website=independent |publisher=Independent |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to prosecutor Michel Bourlet, Zico was charged with truck theft, document forgery and insurance fraud.&lt;ref name="independent"/&gt;

===Judge Van Espens close ties to suspect Michel Nihoul===
The judge presiding of the Dutroux case, Judge Van Espen, had a close relationship to Michel Nihoul. A journalist revealed that as a lawyer Nihoul had represented the wife of Nihoul. Van Espens sister was the godmother of Nihouls child. However even though his close friend Michel Nihoul was involved in the case, Van Espen never resigned. He was also not removed from the case for a very long time. Even though judge Conerotte had been removed simply for attending a fundraising dinner.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Van Espen was further more the judge presiding over the murder case of Christine van Hees from 1984. He only resigned from this case in 1998 when Nihoul was accused of being involved in the murder and van Espens close ties to Nihoul were revealed.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

===Testimony of judge Jean-Marc Connerottes in court===
Judge Connerottes testified in the Dutroux case on 4 March 2004. He broke down in the witness box stating that there had been high-level murder plots to stop his investigation into the child-sex mafia. He stated that he had to drive in bullet-proof cars and had armed guards around him at all times because shadowy figures from the crime world were threatening him. The police had informed him that murder contracts had been taken out against the prosecutors in the case. He alleged that organised crime methods were used to discredit his work and make sure that the investigation would end in a judicial failure.&lt;ref name="telegraphmurder"/&gt;

Connerottes criticised authorities for not rescuing Julie and Melissa even though Dutroux had been a prime suspect for one year before they were found dead. The judge also said that he had received files describing a child-sex network. It described seizure of children and foreign trafficking. The sum of 150.000 Francs was mentioned as the price for a girl.&lt;ref name="telegraphmurder"/&gt; Connerottes also said that he was doubtful about the official explanation on how Julie and Melissa died. It was said that they starved to death in the dungeon. An adult can last about three days without water and maximum 60 days without food. If they received nothing to drink and eat they should have been dead very soon after Dutroux was imprisoned. However Michelle Martin insisted that they were still alive when he returned.&lt;ref name="telegraphmurder"/&gt; Connerottes had even written to King Albert in 1996 stating that his investigations into crime networks were being blocked because suspects "received serious protection". The judge said that the "dysfunctional judiciary" was breaking down as mafia groups took secret control of the "key institutions of the country".&lt;ref name="telegraphmurder"/&gt;

===Letter of judge Jean-Marc Connerottes to King Albert II===
A letter of juge Connerottes addressed to King Albert II in 1996 stated: ''"This institution seems to acquire its authority and supremacy over sectors of the justice system by relying on a complex and secret modus operandi, that of the appropriation of certain key circuits of our institutions created and regulated by the Law. It is a matter essentially of political, financial, police, and media circuits. This mafia-style criminal phenomenon is evidently not peculiar to Belgium, but it involves particular manifestations that are well suited to this small country. We can imagine the obstacles that a judiciary inquiry will meet when investigating such facts: numerous taboos, problems of mentality, and a lack of cultural reference on the issue in order to be able to become aware of or deal with such criminal phenomena, taking advantage in Belgium of official reticence in terms of their acknowledgement, which favours or supports their occultation. The function of a criminal system of this sort is obviously to serve its fundamental purpose, the pursuance of particularly profitable illicit activities, such as money-laundering, and to protect the ‘legitimacy’ of its activities and the impunity of its agents. This indispensable function corresponds to the motive of criminal protection that assures the permanency of the incriminated system by means of the infiltration of the certain circuits of our institutions, especially the police force, a veritable ‘knot’ which my whole investigation has come up against."''&lt;ref name="infrakshun"&gt;{{cite web |title=Jean Michel Nihoul |url=https://infrakshun.wordpress.com/tag/jean-michel-nihoul/ |website=infrakshun.wordpress.com |publisher=Infrakshun |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Book by chairman of the parliamentary inquiry Marc Verwilghen===
Marc Verwilghen, the chairman of the parliamentary inquiry into the handling of the Dutroux case, reported attempts in a book he published in 1999 to stifle their investigation into how the case had been handled. Verwilghen eventually published a book which claimed that the commission’s findings had been muzzled by political and judicial leaders to prevent the revelation of details which would have implicated the complicity of additional perpetrators. Mr Verwilghen claimed that senior political and legal figures refused to cooperate with the inquiry. He said magistrates and police were officially told to refuse to answer certain questions, in what he described as 'a characteristic smothering operation'. Verwilghen blamed Mr Langlois for refusing to hand over evidence of official protection for Mr Dutroux. He said that if they had received that information, their report would have been without doubt more precise and detailed. Verwilghen added that for him, the Dutroux affair was a question of organised crime.&lt;ref name="guardianverwilghen"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Bates |first1=Stephen |title=Cover-up claims revive sex scandal |url=http://archive.is/HNJHi#selection-1095.30-1095.252 |website=theguardian.com |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Statements by senator Anne-Marie Lizin===
The Belgian senator Anne-Marie Lizin commented on the case saying: "''Stupidity (by the police) can't be the only explanation. It's a question of stupidity, incompetence and corruption. Dutroux must be a friend of somebody important. Or else he was being protected because he was known to be a police informant''." Lizin said Dutroux was not a true pedophile, as he has been portrayed. He had a record of dealing in stolen cars, selling arms to hoodlums and trafficking in prostitution. ''"When he discovered that men paid a lot more for little girls for prostitution, he started kidnapping them,"'' she said. When Dutroux finally was arrested, police found in his house video films of him raping little girls. They said he did this so he could sell the films to pedophiles''.''&lt;ref name="chicagotribune"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Moseley |first1=Ray |title=Child Sex Case Adds Outrage To Scandals Rocking Belgium |url=http://archive.is/BOLXi |website=chicagotribune.com |publisher=Chicago Tribune |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attempts to have access to Dutroux Dossier from Wikileaks blocked in Belgium===
In 2009 Wikileaks published the Dutroux Dossier. Belgian authorities tried to have the dossier taken down. The prosecutor general of Liege, Cedric Visart de Bocarme, said “''There is some true, some false, some very disparate information here, involving some people who have done nothing wrong, who have simply been mentioned in an investigation and are thus exposed to public contempt, whereas all this material should have remained classified.''”&lt;ref name="australian"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Charter |first1=David |title=WikiLeaks slammed over publishing dossier including Belgian pedophile killer Marc Dutroux|url=http://archive.is/AyIhz|website=telegraph.co.uk |publisher=The Australian |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Deaths of potential witnesses ===
More than 20 potential witnesses of the case have died with no explanation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2002/may/05/dutroux.featuresreview|title=Belgium's silent heart of darkness|last=Frenkiel|first=Olenka|date=5 May 2002|website=The Guardian|url-status=live|access-date=19 November 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class="wikitable"	
|+	
!Name of the witness	
!Connection to the case	
!Time of death	
!Cause of death	
|-	
|Bernard Weinstein&lt;ref name="rtbf"&gt;{{cite web |title=Les 25 personnages clefs de l'affaire Dutroux: Bernard Weinstein |url=https://www.rtbf.be/info/dossier/l-affaire-dutroux-20-ans-plus-tard/detail_les-25-personnages-clefs-de-l-affaire-dutroux-bernard-weinstein?id=9365628 |website=rtbf.be |publisher=rtbf |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|accomplice of Dutroux	
|November 1995	
|poisoned by Dutroux	
|-	
|Jean Paul-Taminiau&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses3"&gt;{{cite web |title=Marc Dutroux and the dead witnesses 3of3 (English sub) / Marc Dutroux und die toten Zeugen 3von3 |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VFJRo87IZI4&amp;t=20s |website=youtube |publisher=ZDF |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|had rented a garage across a hangar that Dutroux was using	
|2.04.1995 After telling a friend that he received important information about Dutroux	
|His foot was found in a river one year later, the complete corpse was never found	
|-	
|Francois Reyskens&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses3"/&gt;	
|was part of the drug and crime scene, told his father that he wanted to talk to him about Melissa before the public knew about her kidnapping	
|26.07.1995 Before being supposed to testify concerning his knowledge about one of the kidnapped girls, Melissa (died the day he was supposed to testify)	
|Supposed accident (fell in front of a train)	
|-	
|Simon Poncelet&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses3"/&gt;	
|Police men that was investigating the car smuggling ring around Dutroux	
|21.02.1996	
|Was shot during a night shift in his office	
|-	
|Michel Piro&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses3"/&gt;	
|Was a nightclub owner familiar with the redlight scene in Charleroi	
|5.12.1996 Contacted the families of the kidnapped girl Julie and Melissa three months after the arrest of Dutroux	
|Shot on a car parking lot	
|-	
|Joseph Toussaint&lt;ref name="demorgen2"&gt;{{cite web |last1=DDC |title=Alexandre Gosselin |url=https://www.demorgen.be/nieuws/joseph-toussaint-mijnheer-pastoor~b70b68b3/ |website=demorgen.be |publisher=demorgen |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|Confessor of Michelle Martin	
|5.03.1997	
|heart attack	
|-	
|Christiaan Coanrads&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses1"/&gt;
|was a prisoner who was supposed to be questioned about his connections to Dutroux but managed to escape and was found dead one month after the escape
|7.03.1997
|	
|-	
|José Steppe&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses1"/&gt;	
|Well connected person from Charleroi, said that he had important info on Dutroux	
|25.04.1997 Two days before testifying to the police	
|dropped dead ([[Rohypnol]]- a sedative was found in his asthma breathing device)	
|-	
|Brigitte Genard&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses1"/&gt;	
|Friend of Michel Nihoul and dentist	
|5.04.1998- one year after the trial for Dutroux started	
|suicide	
|-	
|Anna Konjevoda&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses1"&gt;{{cite web |title=Marc Dutroux and the dead witnesses 1of3 (English sub) / Marc Dutroux und die toten Zeugen 1von3 |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fuPkoGGm_xQ |website=youtube |publisher=ZDF (2001) |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|Had contacted the police to tell them about connections of a porn ring around Dutroux to Eastern Europe&lt;ref name="mopo"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Dreyer |first1=P. |title=Der angebliche Selbstmord des Dutroux-Staatsanwalts Massa ist nur die Spitze des Eisbergs Die Blutspur des Kinderschänders |url=https://www.mopo.de/der-angebliche-selbstmord-des-dutroux-staatsanwalts-massa-ist-nur-die-spitze-des-eisbergs-die-blutspur-des-kinderschaenders-19186762 |website=mopo |publisher=Hamburger Morgenpost (17.07.99) |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|Found 7.04.1998	
|Beaten, choked and dumped in the river [[Meuse]]	
|-	
|Gina Pardaens&lt;ref name="deadwitnesses2"&gt;{{cite web |title=Marc Dutroux and the dead witnesses 2of3 (English sub) / Marc Dutroux und die toten Zeugen 2von3 |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hqgocOm-omg |website=youtube |publisher=ZDF |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|social worker supporting victims of a child pornography ring, told friends that she saw a child pornography tape in which one girl was murdered and claimed she recognised one of the perpetrators as an acquaintance of Michel Nihoul	
|15.11.1998-After calling the police to tell them that she has been threatened with death (by a car accident) in connection with her work	
|car crash (80&amp;nbsp;km/h into bridge railing)	
|-	
|Sandra Claeys&lt;ref name="demorgen4"&gt;{{cite web |title=Sandra Claeys, Lelièvres grote liefde, pleegde zelfmoord |url=https://www.demorgen.be/nieuws/sandra-claeys-lelievres-grote-liefde-pleegde-zelfmoord~b6b7c0e0/ |website=demorgen.be |publisher=de morgen |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|ex-girlfriend of Lièvre, said that she heard him and Dutroux talk about "a way to make a lot of money"	
|4.11.1999	
|suicide	
|-	
|Nadège Renard&lt;ref name="focus"&gt;{{cite web |last1=van Laere |first1=Saskia |title="Dutroux war kein Einzeltäter" |url=https://www.focus.de/politik/ausland/ausland-dutroux-war-kein-einzeltaeter_aid_189407.html |publisher=Focus |accessdate=1 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|Was an acquaintance of Dutroux	
|Before wanting to give a list of contacts surrounding Dutroux to the authorities April 2001	
|car crash
|-	
|}

===The Abrasax sect with members working at the police force in Charleroi===

In a wooden house of Bernard Weinstein (accomplice of Dutroux) a letter was found from the occult sect "Abrasax", in which a gift for the high priestress (Dominique Kindermans)&lt;ref name="irishtimes"/&gt; was mentioned consisting of 17 girls between the age of 2 and 20 for anal, oral and vaginal sex. It was signed by priest "Anubis". This priest was later identified as Francis Desmedt. Later investigations showed that four police men in Charleroi were also members of the sect, one was even the treasurer.&lt;ref name="spiegel"/&gt; The headquarter of the sect (Institut Abrasax) in Rue Emile Vandervelde 223 Forchies La Marche was raided in 1996 by 150 officers. The television showed police taking away bags of papers, video cassettes and a refrigerator. They also took away black magic ritual implements and human skulls.&lt;ref name="irishtimes"/&gt;

== Parliamentary investigation and escape from custody ==
A 17-month investigation by a parliamentary commission into the Dutroux affair produced a report in February 1998, which concluded that while Dutroux did not have accomplices in high positions in the police and justice systems, as he continued to claim, he profited from [[political corruption|corruption]], sloppiness and incompetence.{{citation needed|date=May 2019}}

==Public outcry==
In October 1996 more than 300.000 Belgians marched through the streets of Brussels after the beloved judge Jean-Marc Connerotte was removed from the case. He was removed for attending a fundraising dinner for the families of the victims, which the court system claimed damaged his impartiality.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; They demanded an investigation and reform of the police and justice system. The protest was called the "[[White March]]".&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt;&lt;ref name="nyt"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Reuters |title=275,000 in Belgium Protest Handling of Child Sex Scandal |url=http://archive.is/SFRGD |website=nytimes.com |publisher=New York Times |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; Judge Jean- Marc Connerotte was beloved by the public because the only two surviving victims were rescued on his initiative, which made him a national hero.&lt;ref name="nyt"/&gt; Protesters were wearing signs that said "Stop the cover-up".&lt;ref name="nyt"/&gt;

To protest the prospect of a conditional release of Marc Dutroux, a "Black March" was organised on the 23rd anniversary of the historic "[[White March]]" protest that was held in Brussels on 20 October 1996. The calls to take part in the march were made after it was made public that a court had approved the request of Michel Lelièvre for conditional release, who was an accomplice of Dutroux and had received a 25-year sentence.&lt;ref name="brusselstimes"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Galindo |first1=Gabriela |title=‘Black march’ to denounce conditional release of serial child killer Dutroux’s accomplice |url=https://www.brusselstimes.com/all-news/belgium-all-news/justice-belgium/71010/black-march-to-denounce-release-of-serial-child-killer-dutrouxs-accomplice/ |website=bruseelstimes.com |publisher=The Brussels Times |accessdate=3 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The guardian reported in 2004 that "''the entire credibility of the current reformist government of Guy Verhofstadt and Belgium's very reputation as a normal civilised country is on the line.''"&lt;ref name="guardianhaunted"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Osborn |first1=Andrew |title=Belgium still haunted by paedophile scandal |url=http://archive.is/glp1s#selection-1187.0-1187.337 |website=theguardian.com |publisher=The Guardian |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Assassination of André Cools===
The assassination of [[André Cools]] took place in 1991. The revelations in the Cools case coincided with the revelations in the Dutroux case and in total made the Belgian public lose trust in their government. Van der Biest was eventually convicted but had already been investigated five years prior as the one who ordered the contract hi on Cools. Due to failures in the investigation he wasn't charged. It was found that several Belgian politicians had been bribed with large sums of money by an Italian helicopter manufacturer, Agusta-Dassault, in exchange for military contracts. This included Belgian secretary general of NATO, [[Willy Claes]]. There were allegations that both the assassination of André Cools and the case surrounding Dutroux showed that organised crime had spread in Belgium and that the institutions weren't efficient in combatting the spread or corruption and organised crime.&lt;ref name="washingtonpost"/&gt;

==Trial==
Dutroux's trial began on 1 March 2004, some seven and a half years after his initial arrest.&lt;ref name="irishtimes.com1"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.irishtimes.com/news/dutroux-trial-to-revive-belgium-s-trauma-1.1133525|title=Dutroux trial to revive Belgium's trauma|date=1 March 2004|work=The Irish Times|accessdate=12 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was a [[jury trial|trial by jury]] and up to 450 people were called upon to testify. The trial took place in [[Arlon]], the capital of the [[Luxembourg (province of Belgium)|Belgian province of Luxembourg]], where the investigations had started. Dutroux was tried for the murders of An Marchal, Eefje Lambrecks and Bernard Weinstein. While admitting the abductions, he denied all three killings, although he had earlier confessed to killing Weinstein.&lt;ref name="irishtimes.com1"/&gt; Dutroux was also charged with a host of other crimes: [[auto theft]], [[Kidnapping|abduction]], [[attempted murder]] and attempted abduction, [[child molestation|molestation]], and three unrelated rapes of women from [[Slovakia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://kriminalistika.eu/muzeumzla/dutroux/dutroux.html Marc Dutroux] at Kriminalstika.eu. Retrieved 12 July 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

Martin was tried as an accomplice, as were Lelièvre and [[:nl:Michel Nihoul|Michel Nihoul]]. To protect the accused, they were made to sit in a glass cage during the trial. In the first week of the trial, photos of Dutroux's face were not allowed to be printed in Belgian newspapers for privacy reasons; this ban remained in force until 9 March.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Siuberski|first=Phillipe|title=Dutroux lashes out at media|url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2004/03/09/1078594307568.html|newspaper=The Age|date=9 March 2004|accessdate=18 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the trial, Dutroux continued to insist that he was part of a Europe-wide [[paedophile]] ring with accomplices among police officers, businessmen, doctors, and even high-level Belgian politicians.&lt;ref name="bbc.co.uk"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-21498535|title=Belgium court denies Marc Dutroux release|work=BBC News|accessdate=12 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a rare move, the [[jury]] at the [[Court of assizes (Belgium)|assizes trial]] publicly protested the presiding judge Stéphane Goux's handling of the debates and the victims' testimonies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.humanite.fr/node/304250 |newspaper=l'Humanité|title=Procès Dutroux. Le président rappelé à l'ordre|trans-title=Dutroux trial. President recalled to order|date=22 April 2004|access-date=19 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 June 2004, after three months of trial, the jury went into seclusion to reach their verdicts on Dutroux and the three other accused. Verdicts were returned on 17 June 2004 after three days of deliberation.&lt;ref name="irishtimes.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.irishtimes.com/news/belgian-paedophile-dutroux-guilty-of-rape-and-murder-1.1145387|title=Belgian paedophile Dutroux guilty of rape and murder|date=18 June 2004|work=The Irish Times|accessdate=12 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dutroux, Martin and Lelièvre were found guilty on all charges; the jury were unable to reach a verdict on Nihoul's role.&lt;ref name="irishtimes.com"/&gt;

===Dutroux's testimony===
Dutroux claimed that he was a low dog in a powerful pedophile network. He further claimed that Michel Nihoul was the organizer of their abductions."&lt;ref name="guardingdungeondeath"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Black |first1=Ian |title=Dutroux boasts of dungeon of death |url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/mar/04/dutroux.ianblack |website=theguardian.com |publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said that he did torture and abuse all of the girls but denied killing any of them until the very end.&lt;ref name="telegraphkill"/&gt; Dutroux further denied the kidnapping, raping and murdering Melissa and Julie. He however admitted to incarcerating them at one of his houses.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; On the case of Melissa and Julie Dutroux also claimed that he had "protected them from a power and sinister child sex ring."&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Black |first1=Ian |title=Dutroux boasts of dungeon of death |url=http://archive.is/z2BV4 |website=theguardian.com |publisher=The Guardian|accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; His testimony that he never raped Julie and Melissa was somewhat supported by examinations of psychiatrists in 1996 stating that Dutroux didn't fit the pedophile profile. He wasn't attracted to children. But might have chosen to abduct younger victims because they were easier to manipulate and control.&lt;ref name="murderpedia"/&gt;
{{check quotation}}
Dutroux admitted to abduction and rape of the other girls. He also admitted to burying his accomplice, Bernard Weinstein, alive for ''"letting the girls die.''"&lt;ref name="telegraphburied"/&gt; Dutroux further said that two unidentified policemen had taken part with him in the kidnapping of An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks.&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt; He boasted about having build the dungeon in which An and Eefje were held for a while. He said: ''"I wanted to create a hiding place to spare them from being sent to a prostitution ring."'' Dutroux admitted to raping Eefje. He said that Weinstein had raped An. He also admitted to drugging both of them. Dutroux also admitted that he kidnapped Sabine Dardenne and raped her. He also admitted to kidnapping and raping Lateita Delhez but not handing them over to Nihoul ‘’"to spare them the fate of An and Eefje."’’&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt; Dutrouxs lawyer, Xavier Magnee, repeatedly said that the prosecution never followed up on evidence of a network surrounding Dutroux.&lt;ref name="telegraphburied"/&gt;

===Michelle Martins testimony===
Martin testified that Dutroux and Weinstein kidnapped Melissa and Julia.&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt; She also said that Dutroux had told her that he had murdered Weinstein.&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt; Martin further said that Dutroux and Weinstein had killed An and Eefje.&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt; She further testified that Melissa and Julie starved to death in their basement in 1996 while Dutroux was in jail. She claims, that she was too scared to descend to the basement.&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt;

Martin said that Dutroux had already decided to abduct girls in 1985. He had said that it was easier to abduct and rape girls than having to start affairs with them. This way he would also have more resources and time to spend on her. So she had to help him with the abductions.&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"/&gt;

===The X files===
The X files were testimonies of people who claimed to have been victims of Marc Dutroux. They had been created after judge Jean-Marc Connerotte had made a public appeal for victims to come forward. In total at least ten victims subsequently contacted the police. All of the witnesses were given the code name "X number". One of the witnesses names, namely X1, was revealed to be [[Regina Louf|Régina Louf]].&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; X1 said that from the age of 11/12 onwards a family friend named Tony Van den Bogaert took her to sex parties with the approval of her family. Several witnesses and family members of Louf confirmed that she had a sexual relationship with Tony Van den Bogaert starting from at least age 12. However Tony Van den Bogaert has never been interrogated, charged or convicted for sexual abuse. She claimed that other minors were present at the sex parties and that those were secretly filmed for [[blackmail]] purposes. She said: ''"It was highly organised. Big business. Blackmail. There was a lot of money involved."'' During her testimony she described some regular clients including judges, a prominent politician and one banker. She gave the police names, addresses and detailed description of two murders that matched unsolved cases of the two murders of teenage girls. Louf said that the parties didn't only include sex but also sadism, torture and murder. She claimed that one of the organisers of the parties was a man she knew as Mich (Jean Michel Nihoul). Louf described him as a cruel man, who sadistically tortured girls.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

Louf said that Marc Dutroux was at that time a young man who brought drugs to the parties for the girls to numb themselves and took care of them in other ways. As a reward he was also allowed to use them for his pleasure.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; The crimes that Louf described took place about ten years prior to the arrest of Dutroux.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Régina Loufs full name was leaked to the press. She was subsequently made out to look like a fantasist and liar.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; The new presiding judges declared that she was not a credible witness and that her testimony and the testimony of the other X witnesses would not be used during the trial.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

One of the other X witnesses, who's real name wasn't revealed, but who's now working for the police said that they had witnessed and experienced similar abuse. They also recounted instances where children were chased through the woods with Dobermans.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt;

Witness X3 testified that one of the people present at the gatherings that involved sex orgies with minors, torture and murder was [[Willy Claes]], secretary general of the NATO. Claes resigned after he was found guilty of corruption in a tendering process for a large defence contract connected to [[Agusta scandal|Agusta helicopters]], a large military-helicopter producer from Italy.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"/&gt;

The testimony of X2 implicated that [[Etienne Davignon]], [[Maurice Lippens (politician)|Maurice Lippens]], [[Paul Vanden Boeynants]], [[Benoît de Bonvoisin|Benoit de Bonvoisin]] and Prince Alexandre of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha were named as having been present at orgies involving underaged nomP.&lt;ref name="infrakshun"/&gt;

A book was published in November 1999 titled: "''The X-Files: What Belgium Was Not Supposed to Know About the Dutroux Affair''." It was written by two journalist from the Flemish Belgian newspaper [[De Morgen]], Annemie Bulte and Douglas De Coninck and another journalist from the French Belgian newspaper Journal du Mardi, Marie-Jeanne Van Heeswyck. It claimed that the X witnesses were much more believable than stated by the media. But it also stated that there had been substantial efforts by the magistrates and senior police officials to demolish the testimony of the X-witnesses. The father of a police officer that was murdered while investigating a car smuggling ring, Judge Guy Poncelet, said that the book was brilliant and convincing. He said he believed that crucial evidence had been down played by the authorities.&lt;ref name="nytimesbook"&gt;{{cite web |last1=James |first1=Barry |title=Belgium Pedophilia Scandal /Did Authorities Cover Up Its Scope?: Book Revives Fear of Grand Conspiracy |url=http://archive.is/Evfkk#selection-2115.96-2115.114 |website=nytimes.com |publisher=The New York Times |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sentencing===
The [[Capital punishment in Belgium|death penalty]] was abolished in Belgium in 1996. The last execution for common-law crimes was in 1918. However, the majority of Belgians, at the time of the trial, would have had no problem with Dutroux receiving the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.volkskrant.nl/buitenland/niet-alle-vragen-over-marc-dutroux-zijn-beantwoord~a691596/ |newspaper=Die Volkskrant |title=Niet alle vragen over Marc Dutroux zijn beantwoord|trans-title=Not all questions about Marc Dutroux are answered|first1=Bart |last1=Dirks|date= 1 March 2004|access-date=19 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 June 2004, Dutroux received the maximum sentence of [[life imprisonment]], while Martin received 30 years and Lelièvre 25 years. The jury was asked to go back into seclusion to decide whether or not Nihoul was an accomplice.{{citation needed|date=May 2019}}

On 23 June, Dutroux lodged an appeal against his sentence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Belgium's Dutroux 'lodges appeal'|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3834499.stm|publisher=BBC News (BBC)|date=23 June 2004|accessdate=18 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Nihoul was [[acquittal|acquitted]] of [[kidnapping]] and [[Conspiracy (crime)|conspiracy]] charges, he was convicted on drug-related charges and was sentenced to five years imprisonment. Nihoul was released in spring 2006. He resided in [[Zeebrugge]] until his death on 23 October 2019.{{citation needed|date=May 2019}}

On 19 August 2012, about 2000 people in Brussels demonstrated against Martin's possible early release from prison. She has since been [[parole]]d, 13 years into her sentence,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Belgians demand pedophile accomplice stays in jail |date=19 August 2012 |url=http://www.sacbee.com/2012/08/19/4739041/belgians-demand-pedophile-accomplice.html |work=Sacbee News }}{{dead link|date=June 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; and was released into the care of the [[Poor Clares]] in [[Malonne]]. She was given shelter, although she was not part of the community. The sisters have declared that they were not her guardian and shelter was given under the condition that she would not violate the conditions of her parole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.ad.nl/buitenland/michelle-martin-onherkenbaar-veranderd~abff3872/ |title='Michelle Martin onherkenbaar veranderd' |trans-title=Michelle Martin irrecognisably changed|date= 30 April 2014|newspaper=Algemeen Dagblad|accessdate=19 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the convent has since been sold, she has had to find new shelter or go back to prison. A former judge has created an apartment in his converted farmhouse, where she now lives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://deredactie.be/cm/vrtnieuws/binnenland/2.31353 Article on the website] of Belgian television and radiostation [[Vlaamse Radio- en Televisieomroeporganisatie|VRT]] (in Dutch): Michelle Martin moves to ex-judge&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://brandpunt.kro-ncrv.nl/brandpunt/oud-rechter-neemt-ex-vrouw-dutroux-in-huis-ik-heb-ruimte-genoeg/ Website article relating to a Dutch TV program (in Dutch)], TV program about the judge who has given Michelle Martin shelter in his converted farm&lt;/ref&gt;

Lelièvre is currently serving his prison sentence in the prison of [[Ittre]]. His application for parole in 2013 was denied.{{citation needed|date=May 2019}} He has since then been granted temporary leave, but has violated the conditions of release. He may be released if he can find an apprenticeship as a cabinet-maker, which has so far been unsuccessful. The Belgian state was forced to pay Lelièvre 6000 [[euro]]s. The [[European Court of Human Rights]] ruled that a moral compensation was in order because he was held in custody (nearly eight years) without receiving answers to his requests.{{citation needed|date=May 2019}}

On 4 February 2013, Dutroux requested the court in Brussels for an early release from prison.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Marc Dutroux: Child Killer Wants Early Release| url=http://news.sky.com/story/1047478/marc-dutroux-child-killer-wants-early-release|publisher=Sky News (BSkyB)|date=4 February 2013|accessdate=18 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He insisted that he was "no longer dangerous" and wanted to be released into [[house arrest]] with an electronic tag ([[Electronic tagging|ankle bracelet]]) placed upon him. On 18 February, the court denied his request.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Belgium court denies Marc Dutroux release|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-21498535|work=BBC News|date=18 February 2013|accessdate=18 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Dutroux is currently being held in solitary confinement in the prison of [[Nijvel|Nivelles]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|trans-title=Marc Dutroux in court on 4 February to get ankle bracelet| title= Marc Dutroux op 4 februari voor strafuitvoeringsrechtbank voor enkelband| work= [[De Standaard]]| url=http://www.standaard.be/artikel/detail.aspx?artikelid=DMF20121227_00415128| date= 27 December 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
	
{| class="wikitable"	
|+	
!Name of suspect	
!Profession	
!Charged with	
!Convicted of	
!Sentence	
!Release	
|-	
|Marc Dutroux	
|unemployed electrician, convicted child kidnapper and rapist	
| Murder (of An and Eefje as well as Bernard Weinstein), rape, kidnapping (of six girls), conspiracy, drug offenses	
| Murder (of An and Eefje as well as Bernard Weinstein), rape, kidnapping (of six girls), conspiracy, drug offenses	
|Life in prison	
|eligible for early release after 30 years in 2021	
|-	
|Michelle Martin	
|housewife	
|Kidnapping, murder of Julie and Melissa	
|Convicted of letting Julie and Melissa starve to death and assisting in the kidnappings	
|30 years imprisonment	
|Released under conditions in 2012 after serving 16 years out of 30&lt;ref name="kriminalistika"/&gt;	
|-	
|Michel Nihoul	
|businessman	
|Kidnapping, conspiracy, gang formation, document fraud, drug trafficking, car smuggling	
|Acquitted of kidnapping, document fraud, trading of stolen vehicles&lt;ref name="nytconvicted"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Smith |first1=Craig |title=Belgian Man Is Convicted Of Raping and Killing Girls |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/18/world/belgian-man-is-convicted-of-raping-and-killing-girls.html |website=nytimes.com |publisher=The New York TImes |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|5 years imprisonment
|Was released early in May 2006 under conditions&lt;ref name="brf"&gt;{{cite web |title=Michel Nihoul wird vorzeitig aus der Haft entlassen |url=https://brf.be/national/6134/ |website=brf.be |publisher=BRF |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Michael Lelièvre	
|drug addict and petty thief	
|Kidnapping, rape, murder	
|Kidnapping of An, Eefje, Sabine and Laetitia and rape	
|25 years imprisonment	
|Was released under conditions in October 2019&lt;ref name="lesoirlelievre"&gt;{{cite web |title=L’avocate de Michel Lelièvre: "Il a mûri, il est prêt à réintégrer la société" |url=https://www.lesoir.be/250659/article/2019-10-01/lavocate-de-michel-lelievre-il-muri-il-est-pret-reintegrer-la-societe |website=lesoir.be |publisher=Le Soir |accessdate=9 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;	
|-	
|}

===Michel Nihoul===
Michel Nihoul was a business man that was known to frequently attend sex parties. He was accused of being the brains behind the child kidnapping and abuse operation around Dutroux.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; Nihoul was charged in relation to the case with "kidnapping, rape, conspiracy and drug offenses."&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt;
Nihouls lawyer in the case was, Frederic Clement de Clety. His lawyer denied all charged made against Nihoul by Dutroux and called him a ‘’"liar and manipulator."’’&lt;ref name="guardiandungeondeath"/&gt; When the investigative journalist, Olenka Frenkiel, met Nihoul in Brussels he reportedly greeted her with the words "I am the monster of Belgium." He told her that he was certain that he would never be prosecuted. During the encounter he grabbed her, tickled her and pulled her unto him so that she called for her colleagues to help her get away from him. Frenkiel was working on a documentary on the case for the BBC.&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt;

===Judges===
* Jean-Marc Connerotte (on his initiative two girls were rescued, was removed from case for attending fundraising dinner for families)
* Judge Jacques Langlois (investigating magistrate). Dutroux case was his first assignment&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; 
* Stephane Goux (judge presiding over verdict)&lt;ref name="telegraphkill"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Evans-Pritchard |first1=Ambrose |title=Why didn't you kill me, child rape victim asks Dutroux |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/belarus/1459791/Why-didnt-you-kill-me-child-rape-victim-asks-Dutroux.html |website=telegraph.co.uk |publisher=telegraph |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Judge Van Espen (was in charge of the murder investigation of Christine van Hees, resigned from the Dutroux case and the murder investigation around van Hees after his close ties to Michel Nihoul were made public in 1998)

==Effects in Belgium==
The Dutroux case is so infamous that more than a third of Belgians with the surname "Dutroux" applied to have their surname changed between 1996 and 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=Belgian paedophile's namesakes change surnames | date=10 January 1998 | url =http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/world/monitoring/46398.stm | work =BBC News | accessdate = 10 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Confirmed victims of Dutroux==
* Sylvie D., 11, 17 October 1985, abducted and raped&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"/&gt;
* Maria V., 19, 17 October 1985, abducted and raped&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"/&gt;
* Catherine B., 18, 17th 1986, abducted and raped&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"/&gt;
* Elisabeth G., 15, 18 December 1985, abducted, raped, Dutroux took videos and pictures of her&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"/&gt;
* Axelle D., 14 December 1985, abducted and raped&lt;ref name="nieuwsblad"/&gt;
* Melissa Russo, 8, 24 June 1995, abducted and imprisoned, died of starvation and dehydration,&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; found in Sars-la-Buissiere
* Julie Lejeune, 8, 24 June 1995, abducted and imprisoned, died of starvation and dehydration,&lt;ref name="guardian"/&gt; found in Sars-la-Buissiere
* An Marchal, 17, 23 August 1995,&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt; abducted, imprisoned and raped, buried alive after being wrapped in plastic,&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt; found August 1996&lt;ref name="telegraphburied"/&gt;
* Eefje Lambrecks, 19, 23 August 1995,&lt;ref name="telegraphcover"/&gt; abducted, imprisoned and raped, buried alive after being wrapped in plastic,&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt; found August 1996&lt;ref name="telegraphburied"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Evans-Pritchard |first1=Ambrose |title=Two girls were buried alive by Dutroux, Belgian court is told |url=http://archive.is/MgQKg |website=telegraph.co.uk |publisher=telegraph |accessdate=8 November 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Sabine Dardenne, 12, 28 May 1996, abducted, chained by neck for 79 days and raped repeatedly&lt;ref name="consortiumnews"/&gt;
* Laetitia Delhez, 14, 9 August 1996, abducted, chained to bed and raped for four days

==Dutroux's houses==
Marc Dutroux owned seven houses, four of which he used for his kidnappings:
*The house on the Route de Philippeville 128 in [[Marcinelle]] is most often cited in the media. All victims were held captive here in the basement and bedroom. The municipality of [[Charleroi]] seized ownership of this house, because of what happened there and the bad state of the house. There are plans to create an open space with a memorial site here. In the Belgian procedure of [[compulsory purchase]], an owner has a last right to visit a house. Therefore, Dutroux visited this house on 10 September 2009, under heavy police guard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://www.standaard.be/Artikel/Detail.aspx?artikelId=4H2F1V1A&amp;subsection=3 |title= Dutroux nog één keer naar huis| 
trans-title= Dutroux even home once| language=Dutch | first=Steven |last= De Bock |work= De Standaard| date= 11 September 2009 | accessdate= 13 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A house in [[Jumet]], that has since been demolished. The remains of An Marchal and Eefje Lambrecks were found buried in the garden of this house. Bernard Weinstein lived in this house for a while. A small monument is placed at this location.
*A house in [[Marchienne-au-Pont]]. Julie Lejeune and Mélissa Russo were held captive here for a short while after their kidnapping.
*A house in [[Sars-la-Buissière]]. The bodies of Lejeune, Russo and Weinstein were found buried in the garden. The house was bought by the municipality of [[Lobbes]] in the first months of 2009. It is planned to make a park with a monument commemorating Dutroux's victims here.
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Maison Marc Dutroux - Avenue Philippeville 128, Marcinelle - murals.jpg|Murals on a wall opposite the house in Marcinelle.
File:Site_du_maison_de_Marc_Dutroux_-_Rue_Daubresse_63,_Jumet.jpg|Location of the house of Dutroux in [[Jumet]].
File:Maison Marc Dutroux - Marchienne-au-Pont.jpg|House owned by Dutroux in [[Marchienne-au-Pont]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Chronology of the case==
===Previous crimes===
* '''April 26, 1989''' - Marc Dutroux is convicted of the rape of five girls in 1985 and 1986.
* '''April 8, 1992''' - Dutroux, thanks to the then minister of justice Melchior Wathelet, is released from prison early where he was serving a 13.5 year sentence.

===Main crimes and arrests===
* '''24 June 1995''' - The eight-year-old girls Julie Lejeune and Mélissa Russo are abducted in Liège.
* '''August 22, 1995''' - The 17-year-old An Marchal and the 19-year-old Eefje Lambrecks are kidnapped in Ostend.
* '''November 25, 1995''' - The 43-year-old Bernard Weinstein was killed by Dutroux (presumably on this date).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.standaard.be/artikel/detail.aspx?artikelid=DEXA23022004_028 De moord waar geen haan naar kraaide], De Standaard, 20 februari 2004&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''December 13, 1995''' - Following tips from witnesses and Dutroux's mother, Chief Guard René Michaux searches Dutroux 's house in Marcinelle . Children's voices are heard, but Michaux thinks that they come from outside.
* '''May 28, 1996''' - 12-year-old Sabine Dardenne is abducted in Kain, Walloon .
* '''August 9, 1996''' - Laetitia Delhez, 14, is abducted in Bertrix .
* '''August 13, 1996''' - Dutroux, his wife Michelle Martin, and a friend, Michel Lelièvre, are arrested on the basis of witness statements.
* '''August 15, 1996''' - Police discovered Sabine Dardenne and Laetitia Delhez, who were hidden in a cell in the basement of Dutroux's house.
* '''August 16, 1996''' - Police arrest Michel Nihoul on suspicion of conspiracy .
* '''August 17, 1996''' - The bodies of Julie and Mélissa are dug up in the garden of a house that Dutroux owns in Sars-la-Buissière. The girls died of starvation . The corpse of Bernard Weinstein, a French companion of Dutroux, is also discovered in the same garden.
* '''August 18, 1996''' - Dutroux and Lelièvre confess the kidnapping of An and Eefje, but deny that the teenagers were murdered.
* '''September 3, 1996''' - The police find the bodies of An and Eefje under a shed at Weinstein's house. They are buried alive.

===Investigation===
* ''''September 21, 1996''' - Jean-Marc Connerotte, investigating judge in the Dutroux case, marries his girlfriend with whom he has been together for 10 years. Together with their son they visit a benefit meeting for the parents of (the) disappeared children. They eat spaghetti during this benefit meeting . Connerotte sat at the table with Michel Bourlet, the attorney at Neufchâteau . He only stayed for an hour and did not speak to Sabine Dardenne. The magistrates received a fountain pen of 27 euros each, their wives a bouquet of flowers.
* '''October 15, 1996''' - The spaghetti affair : the Court of Cassation removes the investigating judge Jean-Marc Connerotte because attending this benefit meeting where he received two gifts (the plate of spaghetti and a fountain pen).
* '''October 20, 1996''' - The White March . Around 300,000 people demonstrate in Brussels to vent their outrage at the delays and errors in the Dutroux investigation.
* '''October 24, 1996''' - Fearing that the Dutroux investigation will be screwed up, the Belgian parliament will set up an independent investigation committee to investigate the Dutroux case, as well as the possible procedural errors in the Belgian police and judicial authorities. Marc Verwilghen will be the chairman .
* '''March 15, 1997''' - The Dutroux commission makes scathing criticism of the police and the Ministry of Justice, who made a mess of investigations into the missing girls.
* '''May 6, 1997''' - The Dutroux Commission returns to work and investigates whether Dutroux was protected by high figures.
* '''February 15, 1998''' - The committee's second report states that the Dutroux gang did not enjoy protection from above, but benefited from corruption, carelessness, and lack of professionalism.
* '''April 23, 1998''' - Dutroux escapes his guards in the Neufchâteau courthouse, but is picked up again four hours later in Herbeumont Saint-Médard by ranger Stéphane Michaux . Interior Minister Johan Vande Lanotte and Minister of Justice Stefaan De Clerck offer their resignation on the same day and are succeeded by Louis Tobback and Tony Van Parys respectively . The head of the government service, Willy Deridder, also resigns.
* '''July 14, 1999'''- Hubert Massa, Advocate General in charge of the Dutroux case, commits suicide.
* '''December 15, 1999''' - Michel Nihoul is released conditionally due to lack of evidence.
* '''March 15, 2002''' - Investigative Judge Jacques Langlois completes the investigation into Dutroux.
* '''January 17, 2003''' - The Council Chamber in Neufchâteau decides to bring Dutroux, Martin and Lelièvre before the Court of Assisen. Nihoul is excluded from prosecution. Public prosecutor Bourlet and some civil parties file an appeal.
* April 30, 2003 - The Liège Chamber of Indictment (AI) follows Attorney Bourlet and also refers Nihoul to the Court of Assisen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.standaard.be/artikel/detail.aspx?artikelid=DST30042003_005 Proces-Dutroux of Dutroux-Nihoul? Gerecht hakt knopen door na bijna zeven jaar], www.standaard.be, 30 april 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.standaard.be/artikel/detail.aspx?artikelid=DMF30042003_002 Nihoul naar assisen], www.standaard.be, 1 mei 2003&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''December 8, 2003''' - Attorney Bourlet files the 27-page indictment.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20071028110022/http://www.observatoirecitoyen.be/IMG/pdf/Acte_d_accusation.pdf Acte d'accusation], Luiks Hof van Beroep, 8 december 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

===Trial===
* '''March 1, 2004''' - The Dutroux trial starts in Arlon .
* '''June 14, 2004''' - After 56 litigation days, the twelve members of the jury withdraw to consider the guilt or innocence of the suspects.
* '''June 17, 2004''' - Dutroux is found guilty of various murders.
* '''June 22, 2004''' - Dutroux is sentenced to life imprisonment and 10 years at the government's disposal . Michelle Martin gets 30 years in prison, Michel Lelièvre 25 years and Michel Nihoul 5 years. Dutroux appeals in cassation.
* '''December 16, 2004''' - The Court of Cassation decides that no procedural errors have been made. The penalties continue to apply.
* '''October 2005''' - Lelièvre asks for a first time to be released conditionally. That is refused because he has not yet reimbursed his victims.&lt;ref name="watmetdutrouxlelievre"&gt;[http://www.standaard.be/artikel/detail.aspx?artikelid=4G39UOAP Wat met Dutroux en Lelièvre?], www.standaard.be, 10 mei 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
* Michel Nihoul was released early in May 2006 under conditions&lt;ref name="brf"/&gt;
* '''2007''' - The Belgian state is ordered by the European Court of Human Rights to pay 6,000 euros in damages to Lelièvre, because his pre-trial detention had lasted unreasonably long. Like Marc Dutroux and Michelle Martin, Lelièvre had been in jail for almost eight years when he was convicted in 2004. The money goes to his victims.&lt;ref name="watmetdutrouxlelievre" /&gt;
* '''April 2007''' - Michelle Martin submits a request for conditional release, in application of the Lejeune Act . This is rejected in view of the seriousness of the facts, the lack of probation prospects and the risks associated with the psychological profile of the convicted person.
* '''October 2008''' - Martin submits a second application, which is rejected.
* '''November 2009''' - Martin submits a third application, which is again rejected.
* '''8 May 2011''' - Martin, after serving half of her sentence, obtains conditional release. The associated conditions were not met in mid-* June 2011, and Martin was not released conditionally.
* '''April 2012''' - Dutroux requests penal leave, allowing him to stay outside the prison for a day and a night every month (this can be done at the earliest one year before serving one third of his sentence). The prison management rejects.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nieuws.vtm.be/binnenland/201209167884-dutroux-vindt-dat-hij-genoeg-heeft-geboet Dutroux vindt dat hij genoeg heeft geboet], www.vtm.be, 16 september 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

===Releases===
* '''July 31, 2012''' - The criminal court decides once again to release Michelle Martin conditionally. The monastery of the Poor Klaren in Malonne is prepared to receive her. However, the Public Prosecution Service appeals in cassation. The conditional release leads to protests.
* '''August 19, 2012''' - The families of Julie Lejeune and An Marchal, together with Laetitia Delhez, are organizing a manifestation against Martin's conditional release. There are 5000 participants. After the event, they will be received by Minister of Justice Annemie Turtelboom and Minister of Internal Affairs Joëlle Milquet, a week later by Prime Minister Elio Di Rupo .
* '''August 28, 2012''' - The Supreme Court ruled that it had found no procedural errors in the decision of the criminal court. A few hours later Martin leaves the prison on the way to the monastery in Malonne.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deredactie.be/cm/vrtnieuws/binnenland/120828_MichelleMartin Hof van Cassatie bevestigt vrijlating van Martin], www.deredactie.be, 28 augustus 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deredactie.be/cm/vrtnieuws/binnenland/120828_MichelleMartin_Malonne Michelle Martin is aangekomen in Malonne], www.deredactie.be, 28 augustus 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''September 6, 2012''' - Following the protests against the release of Martin, the government summit concretises the coalition agreement that included a sensitive tightening of the conditional release.&lt;ref&gt;''Zwaar gestraften blijven langer in de cel'', De Standaard, 6 september 2012, p. 8-9&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''13 September 2012''' - Dutroux applies for release with ankle strap (this can be done six months before the first appearance before the criminal court).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.deredactie.be/permalink/1.1430170 Dutroux wil met enkelband vrijkomen], VRT Journaal 7u, www.deredactie.be, 14 september 2012&lt;/ref&gt; According to Ronny Baudewijn, Dutroux's lawyer, he also really hopes to be released. He declares to have spent hours discussing repentance and regret with him, which Dutroux does not have: He finds it regrettable that people have died, but he does not feel guilty. As a psychopath, he cannot empathize with what he does to others, he only sees what he is entitled to .&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.standaard.be/artikel/detail.aspx?artikelid=DMF20120914_196 Advocaat wist niet dat Dutroux aanvraag voor enkelband indiende], www.standaard.be, 14 september 2012&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''April 2013''' - Dutroux will have served one third of his sentence and will be summoned for the first time by the enforcement court (even if he does not take the initiative with a request for a conditional release).
* Michael Lelièvre was released under conditions in '''October 2019'''&lt;ref name="lesoirlelievre"/&gt;
* '''In October 2019''' Dutroux filed to have himself be examined by psychiatrist. In order to be able to be released early under conditions in 2021 three psychiatrists would have to come to the conclusion that the danger of him reoffending is low.&lt;ref name="nytimespsy"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Peltier |first1=Elian |title=Notorious Killer’s Bid for Parole Reopens Old Wounds in Belgium |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/29/world/europe/marc-dutroux-release-parole.html |website=nytimes.com |publisher=New York Times |accessdate=25 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="sudinfo"&gt;{{cite web |title=Demande de libération de Marc Dutroux: l’audience devant le TAP est terminée, une décision sur l’expertise psychiatrique rendue le 28 octobre |url=https://www.sudinfo.be/id146954/article/2019-10-17/demande-de-liberation-de-marc-dutroux-laudience-devant-le-tap-est-terminee-une |website=sudinfo.be |publisher=Sud Info |accessdate=25 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Jean-Denis Lejeune]]
* [[Carine Russo]]
* The [[Alcàsser Girls]]
* [[List of prison escapes]]
* [[Moors murders]]
* [[Sachsensumpf]]
* [[Death of Katrien De Cuyper]]
* [[Regina Louf]]

==References==
; Inline citations
{{Reflist}}

; General references
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20040311052235/http://www.just.fgov.be/proces-arlon/en/arlon-trial.html The official indictment]
*[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/2795545.stm BBC News on Sabine Dardenne]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060107144312/http://www.crimelibrary.com/serial_killers/predators/dutroux/evil_1.html Dutroux at CrimeLibrary]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070205201327/http://www.unhchr.ch/Huridocda/Huridoca.nsf/TestFrame/6643e3a189372013c12566080033e53e?Opendocument United Nations High Commission on Human Rights report criticizing changes in the Belgian Constitution due to the case]

== External links ==
*{{Commons category-inline}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dutroux, Marc}}
[[Category:1956 births]]
[[Category:20th-century Belgian criminals]]
[[Category:Belgian escapees]]
[[Category:Belgian murderers of children]]
[[Category:Belgian people convicted of child sexual abuse]]
[[Category:Belgian people convicted of kidnapping]]
[[Category:Belgian people convicted of murder]]
[[Category:Belgian prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment]]
[[Category:Belgian rapists]]
[[Category:Belgian serial killers]]
[[Category:Drug dealers]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Male serial killers]]
[[Category:People convicted of child pornography offenses]]
[[Category:People convicted of murder by Belgium]]
[[Category:People convicted of theft]]
[[Category:People from Ixelles]]
[[Category:People with antisocial personality disorder]]
[[Category:Political scandals in Belgium]]
[[Category:Prisoners sentenced to life imprisonment by Belgium]]
[[Category:Scandals in Belgium]]
[[Category:Walloon people]]</text>
      <sha1>d8ixn19a1trp0ljxlk9y6jimrlactv8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
